<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ITProCloud Blog</title>
    <description>Welcome to my blog. I&apos;m writing this blog to share my experiences mainly in IT focused on Microsoft Azure. The blog is part of the ITProCloud GmbH.</description>
    <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.itprocloud.de/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 10:25:59 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 10:25:59 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>AVD Need Assistance - NAT shape is Undetermined when probing turn:20.202.248.2:3478?Udp TURN relay health check failed ...</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;current-issues-avd-agent-reports-an-issue-and-brings-the-hosts-into-strongneed-assistancestrong&quot;&gt;Current issues: AVD agent reports an issue and brings the hosts into &lt;strong&gt;“Need Assistance”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last September week, I got a lot of emails and team messages. Customers are seeing the following error message on session hosts in the Azure Portal and in Hydra:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NAT shape is Undetermined when probing [turn:20.202.248.2:3478?Udp] TURN relay health check failed for server [turn:20.202.248.2:3478?Udp] - One or more errors occurred.-&amp;gt;Timed out waiting for Receive to complete - Code: -2147467259 - 2024-09-26T07:39:15.704086Z&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session hosts are also going into the &lt;strong&gt;“Need Assistance”&lt;/strong&gt; mode - even if users can still log in and continue working. It’s also reported, that the time stamp of the error message stays.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue is related to the AVD agent testing a UDP connection to the given (Microsoft) IP. This is a normal behaviour and can fail if customers are not allowing this connection through the firewall. If that is not working, connections are made via TCP. So far - so good. Unfortunately, the AVD agent shows this as an error, bringing the host into the &lt;strong&gt;“Need Assistance”&lt;/strong&gt; mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important: Session hosts in this state do not count on the capacity of a pool in Hydra. It also can break autoscaling if you run Hydra version 1.0.8.5 or less. Also hosts in this state are &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; deallocated automatically - they stay running until the error disappears.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/NA-Hydra.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-we-do&quot;&gt;What can we do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;allowing-udp-communication-to-specific-ports-preferred&quot;&gt;Allowing UDP communication to specific ports (preferred)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can configure the firewall to allow communication to the mentioned ports if that is an option for your environment/company. In short, the following communication from the hosts to the internet must be possible:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Target: 20.202.0.0/16, Port 3478 UDP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Target: 20.202.0.0/16, Port 443 TCP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/rdp-shortpath?tabs=public-networks&quot;&gt;Link to the blog post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can test the connection with the tool &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/troubleshoot-rdp-shortpath&quot;&gt;avdnettest.exe&lt;/a&gt; from Microsoft:
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/NA-avdnettest.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-hydra&quot;&gt;Update Hydra&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a new release of Hydra available from 09/26/2024 (v1.0.8.6) containing a hotfix to handle failed hosts. This will not remove the error message but should show the correct sessions and handle autoscaling also for hosts in the &lt;strong&gt;“Need Assistance”&lt;/strong&gt; mode. Please monitor your environment after update/hotfix: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra?tab=readme-ov-file#updates-and-releases&quot;&gt;How to update Hydra&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;disabling-udp-temporary-workaround&quot;&gt;Disabling UDP temporary (workaround)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If option one is not possible, or the error messages are not disappearing, we can disable the use of UDP &lt;a href=&quot;https://admx.help/?Category=Windows_10_2016&amp;amp;Policy=Microsoft.Policies.TerminalServer::TS_SELECT_TRANSPORT&quot;&gt;via GPO&lt;/a&gt; or reg keys. The following script disables UDP, and it should also remove the error message. You can &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra/blob/main/README.md#scripts-and-script-collections&quot;&gt;create the script in Hydra&lt;/a&gt; and run it on the hosts (test it with one host first):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;New-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\SOFTWARE\Policies\Microsoft\Windows NT\Terminal Services&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;SelectTransport&amp;quot; -Value 1 -force # default: 0

# Reset old failure state
if (Test-Path -Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\RDInfraAgent\HealthCheckReport&amp;quot;) {
    Remove-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\RDInfraAgent\HealthCheckReport&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;AgentHealthCheckReport&amp;quot; -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
    Remove-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\RDInfraAgent\HealthCheckReport&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;AgentHealthCheckTimestamp&amp;quot; -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you rollout a new host, make sure to reapply this settings. That can be done in Hydra -&amp;gt; Host Pool -&amp;gt; New Session Host Rollout -&amp;gt; Run script or script collection after deployment
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s also a good idea to open a ticket to let Microsoft fix this issue with the service/AVD agent.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Need-Assistance-NAT-shape-is-Undetermined-when-probing-TURN-relay-health-check-failed/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Need-Assistance-NAT-shape-is-Undetermined-when-probing-TURN-relay-health-check-failed/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CountrySwitch - First Logon Experience and language selector and an app starter for remote apps on network paths for AVD</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-logon-experience-and-language-selector-and-an-app-starter-for-remote-apps-on-network-paths&quot;&gt;First Logon Experience and language selector and an app starter for remote apps on network paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/CountrySwitch.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 09/16/2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;select-the-language-users&quot;&gt;Select the language (users)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some environments, customers are running Azure on Windows 10/11 with multiple language packs installed. After the first login, users have to choose their language to customize the environment - that is not so easy, while users have to open the language settings and select the language. The first steps are outside the user’s language and are not easy to do for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built a tool that makes it easier for users to select their language by clicking on the right flag. Currently, the following features are available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature regarding the language selection:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tool shows the installed language packages by a flag of the countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A welcome message in the present language welcomes the users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user selects the language settings with a click on the flag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hovering the mouse over a flag shows the country and language name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The app configures the language settings (and does one logoff to apply the setting).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The PowerShell script CountrySwitch-User.ps1 in the program files folder is started to do some optional customizing (language code is in $languageTag)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CountrySwitch is linked in all users’ start menu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startup: With parameter /RunOnce - Starts CountrySwitch at logon. The user will see the language selector only if the user is new and didn’t select a language once (HKCU:\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\CountrySwitch\Completed is set to 1 )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Direct: Without parameters - Users can star CountrySwitch manually to select the language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note on Remote Apps&lt;/strong&gt;: Remote apps are ignoring the autostart folder. To have CountrySwitch enabled for remote app, please configure a local Startup script (local policy for users) with the following parameters:
Name of script: “C:\Program Files\ITProCloud.de\CountrySwitch\CountrySwitch.exe”
Parameters:	/runonce&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;app-starter-for-remote-apps&quot;&gt;App Starter for remote apps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CountrySwitch can also start a local or an application on a file share (which normally does not work directly with AVD). Publish CountrySwitch as a remote app with the following parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CountrySwitch.exe /remoteapp &amp;quot;&amp;lt;path to executable with parameters&amp;gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&amp;lt;Working directory&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CountrySwitch.exe /remoteapp &amp;quot;\\&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;share&amp;gt;\finance.exe /db=vm1&amp;quot; &amp;quot;\\&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;share&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a remote app is started with CountrySwitch, CountrySwitch first starts the PowerShell script CountrySwitch-App.ps1 in the program files folder to do some optional customization. The following parameters are set in the script:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$languageTag = &amp;quot;unknown&amp;quot;,
$appCommandline = &amp;quot;\\&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;share&amp;gt;\finance.exe /db=vm1&amp;quot;,
$appWorkingDir = &amp;quot;\\&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;share&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,
$appParameter = &amp;quot;/db=vm1&amp;quot;,
$appExecutable = &amp;quot;finance.exe&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application starts after the PowerShell script finishes (CountrySwitch will run hidden and terminates after the start of the application (e.g., finance.exe).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;logging-and-configuration&quot;&gt;Logging and configuration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CountrySwitch logs into %AppData%\ITProCloud&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are the following reg keys to optionally configure CountrySwitch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HKLM:\SOFTWARE\Policies\ITProCloud\CountrySwitch (alls values are dword - 1 is true; 0 is false)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Default value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Enabled&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If false, the application will not show up (except for /remoteapp (App starter mode))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ExitOnRunOnceCompleted&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If the app is started with /runonce and the user has already completed the process, the application will not show up&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ExitOnSingleLanguage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If only one language is installed, don’t show up&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LogoffUserAfterSelectingNewLanguage logoff user after selecting a new language&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LogoffUserAfterSelectingSameLanguage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Logoff user after selecting the same language as the user is still using&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;false&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RunUserScriptAfterSelectingLanguage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Runs the ps script CountrySwitch-User.ps1 -languageTag {xx-YY} after the user selects a language&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;DisableUserScriptForAppStarterMode&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If true, the app starter mode for a remote app will no longer trigger CountrySwitch-App before starting the application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;release-notes&quot;&gt;Release notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Release&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Changes &amp;amp; Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-04&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Initial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Update: CountrySwitch-User.ps1 had a typo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Avoid showing MSI installation screen for users if package unaccessible&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-09-16&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Prevents that the logoff message is shown multiple times if the user multiple clicks on a flag&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/CountrySwitch.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 09/16/2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to send me ideas for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/CountrySwitch-Select-Language-on-first-start-and-an-appstarter-for-remoteapps/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/CountrySwitch-Select-Language-on-first-start-and-an-appstarter-for-remoteapps/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Improve AVD User Experience: Warm-Up to decreas User login time</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If you are running Azure Virtual Desktop with FSLogix, the first login to a host takes longer than the following logins. I also wrote about this effect (I call is Cold vs. Warm start) a few weeks ago here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://lnkd.in/eEQHP5gA&quot;&gt;https://lnkd.in/eEQHP5gA&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/marcelmeurer_azurevirtualdesktop-coldstart-warmstart-activity-7227298731124019200--nsM&quot;&gt;https://www.linkedin.com/posts/marcelmeurer_azurevirtualdesktop-coldstart-warmstart-activity-7227298731124019200--nsM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, If a VM is started in Azure, the first login of a user takes much longer than the login of the following users to this VM. And: It makes no difference if the first user logs in one or 30 minutes after starting the VM. I did a lot of tests by running &lt;em&gt;ProcMon, FileActivityWatch, and RegistryChangesView&lt;/em&gt; in the system context to capture events during the first login 🤓. I can clearly see dependencies to AppX packages on the VM. In my tests, processing of AppX packages for the first user took 120 seconds, and for the next user, only a few seconds. Right now, I cannot reproduce the first AppX processing without a user logging into the host (but I’m working on that). The first user will also see a black screen during the login.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I did another test: Create a temporary local user on the VM directly after the start and make a login (autogenerated passwords and direct deletion of the users after the login).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result is as expected: After the start of the VM, the warmup user triggers the AppX processing and other “initializations.” The next - regular - user experiences a much faster login while that is technically the second login for the VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a script to automate a local logon after each VM/host’s start. That may not be the best way to handle this solution, but it is a workaround until I find a more pragmatic solution without a warm-up user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/AVD-UX-WarmUp-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/AVD-UX-WarmUp-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-does-it-work&quot;&gt;How does it work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script is started directly after the start of a VM/host and runs in the context of the computer. The following steps happen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Temporarily, allow RDS logon without validation computer certificates (only for the system account)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generate a local user (warm-up user) with a random password. The account automatically expires after 10 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the user to the Remote Desktop User Group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure the sign-on via RDS to localhost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The warm-up user connects via RDS to localhost (the first user logon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wait 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logoff the user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the user account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the user profile from disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some additional error-handling routines in the script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pro tip:&lt;/strong&gt; If you ever search for a way to get session information with PowerShell without parsing qwinsta.exe or quser.exe, check the script. It also contains a PowerShell method to log off a specific session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;install-the-warm-up-user-script&quot;&gt;Install the warm-up user script&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can install the script on an existing host or on your Golden Master / Template VM (which you hopefully capture loss-less with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt;). Copy the script to the VM and run the following command in an administrative PowerShell:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.\WarmUp.ps -Mode Install&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This copies the script to C:\windows\WarmUp.ps1 and creates a scheduled task to start the script automatically with the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-script&quot;&gt;The script&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Save it as WarmUp.ps1 or download it from here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/MarcelMeurer/1044690ed2619c145305e8cc335948a5&quot;&gt;WarmUp.ps1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;param(
	[string] $Mode
)

Add-Type -Language CSharp -TypeDefinition @&apos;
using System;
using System.Linq;
using System.Runtime.InteropServices;
using System.Collections.Generic;
namespace Rds {
    public static class Sessions {
        [DllImport(&amp;quot;wtsapi32.dll&amp;quot;)]
        static extern IntPtr WTSOpenServer([MarshalAs(UnmanagedType.LPStr)] String pServerName);
        [DllImport(&amp;quot;wtsapi32.dll&amp;quot;)]
        static extern void WTSCloseServer(IntPtr hServer);
        [DllImport(&amp;quot;wtsapi32.dll&amp;quot;)]
        static extern Int32 WTSEnumerateSessions(IntPtr hServer,
            [MarshalAs(UnmanagedType.U4)] Int32 Reserved,
            [MarshalAs(UnmanagedType.U4)] Int32 Version, ref IntPtr ppSessionInfo,
            [MarshalAs(UnmanagedType.U4)] ref Int32 pCount);
        [DllImport(&amp;quot;wtsapi32.dll&amp;quot;)]
        static extern void WTSFreeMemory(IntPtr pMemory);
        [DllImport(&amp;quot;Wtsapi32.dll&amp;quot;)]
        static extern bool WTSQuerySessionInformation(System.IntPtr hServer, int sessionId, WTS_INFO_CLASS wtsInfoClass, out System.IntPtr ppBuffer, out uint pBytesReturned);
        [DllImport(&amp;quot;Wtsapi32.dll&amp;quot;)]
        static extern bool WTSLogoffSession(System.IntPtr hServer, int sessionId, bool wait);
        [StructLayout(LayoutKind.Sequential)]
        private struct WTS_SESSION_INFO {
            public Int32 SessionID;
            [MarshalAs(UnmanagedType.LPStr)]
            public String pWinStationName;
            public WtsConnect State;
        }
        public enum WTS_INFO_CLASS {
            WTSInitialProgram,
            WTSApplicationName,
            WTSWorkingDirectory,
            WTSOEMId,
            WTSSessionId,
            WTSUserName,
            WTSWinStationName,
            WTSDomainName,
            WTSConnectState,
            WTSClientBuildNumber,
            WTSClientName,
            WTSClientDirectory,
            WTSClientProductId,
            WTSClientHardwareId,
            WTSClientAddress,
            WTSClientDisplay,
            WTSClientProtocolType,
            WTSIdleTime,
            WTSLogonTime,
            WTSIncomingBytes,
            WTSOutgoingBytes,
            WTSIncomingFrames,
            WTSOutgoingFrames,
            WTSClientInfo,
            WTSSessionInfo,
            WTSSessionInfoEx,
            WTSConfigInfo,
            WTSValidationInfo,
            WTSSessionAddressV4,
            WTSIsRemoteSession
        }
        public enum WtsConnect {
            Active,
            Connected,
            ConnectQuery,
            Shadow,
            Disconnected,
            Idle,
            Listen,
            Reset,
            Down,
            Init
        }
        public class WtsSessionInformation {
            public string InitialProgram;
            public string ApplicationName;
            public string WorkingDirectory;
            public string OEMId;
            public int SessionId;
            public string UserName;
            public string WinStationName;
            public string DomainName;
            public WtsConnect ConnectState;
            public string ConnectStateString;
            public int ClientBuildNumber;
            public string ClientName;
            public string ClientDirectory;
        }
        public static IntPtr OpenServer(String name) {
            IntPtr server = WTSOpenServer(name);
            return server;
        }
        public static void CloseServer(IntPtr serverHandle) {
            WTSCloseServer(serverHandle);
        }
        public static bool LogoffSession(int id, bool waitForLogoff) {
            IntPtr serverHandle = IntPtr.Zero;
            serverHandle = OpenServer(Environment.MachineName);
            IntPtr sessionInfoPtr = IntPtr.Zero;
            try {
                return WTSLogoffSession(serverHandle, id, waitForLogoff);
            } catch (Exception e) {
                Console.WriteLine(&amp;quot;Exception querying session information: &amp;quot; + e.ToString());
            } finally {
                WTSFreeMemory(sessionInfoPtr);
                CloseServer(serverHandle);
            }
            return false;
        }
        public static WtsSessionInformation GetSession(string userName) {
            var sessions=GetSessions();
            return sessions.FirstOrDefault(n=&amp;gt;string.Equals(n.UserName, userName, StringComparison.InvariantCultureIgnoreCase));
            
        }
        public static List &amp;lt; WtsSessionInformation &amp;gt; GetSessions() {
            var wtsList = new List &amp;lt; WtsSessionInformation &amp;gt; ();
            IntPtr serverHandle = IntPtr.Zero;
            serverHandle = OpenServer(Environment.MachineName);
            IntPtr sessionInfoPtr = IntPtr.Zero;
            try {
                IntPtr sPtr = IntPtr.Zero;
                Int32 sessionCount = 0;
                Int32 retVal = WTSEnumerateSessions(serverHandle, 0, 1, ref sessionInfoPtr, ref sessionCount);
                Int32 dataSize = Marshal.SizeOf(typeof(WTS_SESSION_INFO));
                Int64 currentSession = (long) sessionInfoPtr;
                uint bytes = 0;
                if (retVal != 0) {
                    for (int i = 0; i &amp;lt; sessionCount; i++) {
                        WTS_SESSION_INFO si = (WTS_SESSION_INFO) Marshal.PtrToStructure((System.IntPtr) currentSession, typeof(WTS_SESSION_INFO));
                        currentSession += dataSize;
                        var wts = new WtsSessionInformation();
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSUserName, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.UserName = Marshal.PtrToStringAnsi(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSDomainName, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.DomainName = Marshal.PtrToStringAnsi(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSWinStationName, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.WinStationName = Marshal.PtrToStringAnsi(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSSessionId, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.SessionId = Marshal.ReadInt32(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSInitialProgram, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.InitialProgram = Marshal.PtrToStringAnsi(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSApplicationName, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.ApplicationName = Marshal.PtrToStringAnsi(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSWorkingDirectory, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.WorkingDirectory = Marshal.PtrToStringAnsi(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSConnectState, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.ConnectState = (WtsConnect) Marshal.ReadInt32(sPtr);
                            wts.ConnectStateString = wts.ConnectState.ToString();
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSClientBuildNumber, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.ClientBuildNumber = Marshal.ReadInt32(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSClientName, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.ClientName = Marshal.PtrToStringAnsi(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (WTSQuerySessionInformation(serverHandle, si.SessionID, WTS_INFO_CLASS.WTSClientDirectory, out sPtr, out bytes)) {
                            wts.ClientDirectory = Marshal.PtrToStringAnsi(sPtr);
                            WTSFreeMemory(sPtr);
                        }
                        if (!string.IsNullOrEmpty(wts.UserName)) wtsList.Add(wts);
                    }
                }
                return wtsList;
            } catch (Exception e) {
                Console.WriteLine(&amp;quot;Exception querying session information: &amp;quot; + e.ToString());
            } finally {
                WTSFreeMemory(sessionInfoPtr);
                CloseServer(serverHandle);
            }
            return null;
        }
    }
}
&apos;@

$LogDir=&amp;quot;$($env:windir)\system32\LogFiles&amp;quot;
$LogFile=&amp;quot;$($LogDir)\AVD.WarmUp.log&amp;quot;
function LogWriter($message) {
	$message = &amp;quot;$(Get-Date ([datetime]::UtcNow) -Format &amp;quot;o&amp;quot;) $message&amp;quot;
	write-host($message)
	if ([System.IO.Directory]::Exists($LogDir)) { try { write-output($message) | Out-File $LogFile -Append } catch {} }
}

if ($mode -like &amp;quot;install&amp;quot;) {
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Copy script to windir&amp;quot;)
    Copy-Item &amp;quot;$($MyInvocation.InvocationName)&amp;quot; -Destination ($env:windir + &amp;quot;\WarmUp.ps1&amp;quot;) 

    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Creating schedule task to run the script at startup&amp;quot;)
    $action = New-ScheduledTaskAction -Execute &amp;quot;$env:windir\System32\WindowsPowerShell\v1.0\Powershell.exe&amp;quot; -Argument &amp;quot;-executionPolicy Unrestricted -File `&amp;quot;$($env:windir)\WarmUp.ps1`&amp;quot;&amp;quot;
    $trigger = New-ScheduledTaskTrigger	-AtStartup
    $principal = New-ScheduledTaskPrincipal &apos;NT Authority\SYSTEM&apos; -RunLevel Highest
    $settingsSet = New-ScheduledTaskSettingsSet
    $task = New-ScheduledTask -Action $action -Principal $principal -Trigger $trigger -Settings $settingsSet 
    Register-ScheduledTask -TaskName &apos;ITPC-AVD-WarmUpUser&apos; -InputObject $task -ErrorAction Ignore
    Enable-ScheduledTask -TaskName &apos;ITPC-AVD-WarmUpUser&apos;
} else {

    $localUserName = &amp;quot;warmup-user&amp;quot;

    $characters = &apos;abcdefghijklmnopqrstuvwxyzABCDEFGHIJKLMNOPQRSTUVWXYZ0123456789!@#&apos; #$%^&amp;amp;*()-_=+[]{}|;:,.&amp;lt;&amp;gt;?&apos;
    $localUserPWPlain = -join (1..32 | ForEach-Object { Get-Random -InputObject $characters.ToCharArray() }) +&amp;quot;!@1aA&amp;quot;

    $localUserPW =  ConvertTo-SecureString -String $localUserPWPlain -AsPlainText -Force # https://www.sharepointdiary.com/2020/04/powershell-generate-random-password.html


    # Store default configuration
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Getting local configuration to use saved credentials for the warmup user&amp;quot;)
    $oldAuthenticationLevelOverride=$null
    if (Test-Path &amp;quot;HKCU:\Software\Microsoft\Terminal Server Client&amp;quot;) {
        $oldAuthenticationLevelOverride = Get-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKCU:\Software\Microsoft\Terminal Server Client&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;AuthenticationLevelOverride&amp;quot; -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
    } else {
        New-Item -Path &amp;quot;HKCU:\Software\Microsoft\Terminal Server Client&amp;quot; -Force -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
    }
    if ($oldAuthenticationLevelOverride -eq $null) {$oldAuthenticationLevelOverride = 99} else {$oldAuthenticationLevelOverride = $oldAuthenticationLevelOverride.AuthenticationLevelOverride}


    try {
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Modifying configuration to login warmup user with stored credentials&amp;quot;)
        # Set temporary configuration to allow user logins
        New-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKCU:\Software\Microsoft\Terminal Server Client&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;AuthenticationLevelOverride&amp;quot; -Value 0 -Force
        New-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\Software\Policies\Microsoft\Windows NT\Terminal Services&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;DisablePasswordSaving&amp;quot; -Value 1 -Force

        # Prepare temporary local user
        if ((Get-LocalUser -Name $localUserName -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue) -ne $null) {
            LogWriter(&amp;quot;Removing existing local warmup user&amp;quot;)
            Remove-LocalUser -Name $localUserName
        }
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Adding local user&amp;quot;)
        $localUser = New-LocalUser -Name $localUserName -Password $localUserPW -AccountExpires (Get-Date).AddMinutes(10) -PasswordNeverExpires -UserMayNotChangePassword
        # Add user to remote desktop group
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Adding user to the remote desktop group&amp;quot;)
        Add-LocalGroupMember -SID &amp;quot;S-1-5-32-555&amp;quot; -Member $localUserName -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue

        # Login user
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Adding credentials of the warmup user to the key store&amp;quot;)
        cmdkey /generic:TERMSRV/localhost /user:&amp;quot;$($env:Computername)\$($localUserName)&amp;quot; /pass:$localUserPWPlain
        $startTime=Get-Date


	$i=0
	do {
            LogWriter(&amp;quot;Login in user warmup user&amp;quot;)
            if ($mstsc) {
		$mstsc.Kill()
		Start-Sleep -Seconds 6
	    }
            $mstsc = Start-Process -PassThru -FilePath &amp;quot;mstsc.exe&amp;quot; -ArgumentList &amp;quot;/v:localhost&amp;quot;
    
            # Wait for the user to login 
            LogWriter(&amp;quot;Waiting a few seconds&amp;quot;)
            Start-Sleep -Seconds 20
            $i++		
	} while ([Rds.Sessions]::GetSession($localUserName) -eq $null -and $i -le 10)

        # Remove credentials
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Removing credentials from the key store&amp;quot;)
        cmdkey /delete:TERMSRV/localhost

        # Check, if user is connected
        $session=[Rds.Sessions]::GetSession($localUserName)

        if ($session -eq $null) {
            LogWriter(&amp;quot;Warning: Warm-up user is not connected. So, the workaround is not working for some reasons&amp;quot;)
        } else {
            # Let the user for a while in the session and then logoff
            LogWriter(&amp;quot;Let the user logged in for a while&amp;quot;)
            Start-Sleep -Seconds 300
            LogWriter(&amp;quot;Logoff user&amp;quot;)
            [Rds.Sessions]::LogoffSession($session.SessionId, $true)
            # Remove profile of the user
            try {
                LogWriter(&amp;quot;Delete profile of the warm-up user&amp;quot;)
                @(Get-CimInstance -Class Win32_UserProfile | Where-Object { $_.Loaded -eq $false -and ($_.LocalPath.split(&apos;\&apos;)[-1] -like $localUserName -or $_.LocalPath.split(&apos;\&apos;)[-1] -like &amp;quot;$($localUserName).*&amp;quot;)}) | Remove-CimInstance

            } catch {
                LogWriter(&amp;quot;Error: Cannot delete the profile of the warmup user: $_&amp;quot;)
            }

        }
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Terminate mstsc.exe, if running&amp;quot;)
        $mstsc.Kill()
    } catch {
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Error: $_&amp;quot;)
    } finally {
        # Remove user
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Disable and remove user&amp;quot;)
        Remove-LocalGroupMember -SID &amp;quot;S-1-5-32-555&amp;quot; -Member $localUserName
        Disable-LocalUser -Name  $localUserName -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
        Remove-LocalUser -Name $localUserName -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue

        # Restore default configuration
        LogWriter(&amp;quot;Restoring local configuration&amp;quot;)
        if ($oldAuthenticationLevelOverride -eq 99) {
            Remove-ItemProperty &amp;quot;HKCU:\Software\Microsoft\Terminal Server Client&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;AuthenticationLevelOverride&amp;quot; -Force
        } else {
            New-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKCU:\Software\Microsoft\Terminal Server Client&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;AuthenticationLevelOverride&amp;quot; -Value $oldAuthenticationLevelOverride -Force
        }
    }
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Done&amp;quot;)
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-User-Experience-WarmUp-Script-To-Improve-User-Login-Logon-Time/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-User-Experience-WarmUp-Script-To-Improve-User-Login-Logon-Time/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Windows Update API issue - Exception from HRESULT: 0x8002802B (TYPE_E_ELEMENTNOTFOUND)</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Windows gives you access to work with Windows Update on an API level. This is often used to find, download, and install new updates programmatically. That makes special sense in Azure Virtual Desktop, which allows us to trigger Windows Updates in a maintenance Windows where autoscale is disabled (I don’t want to imagine what happens if Windows shuts down during Windows Updates).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, my solution, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt;, uses the API to install Windows updates. That also includes draining, starting, installing, rebooting, etc. - all that is needed to update an existing host or a golden master. E.g.: Example of the script collection for an update:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WSUS-API-05.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, a Microsoft patch broke the functionality of the Windows Update API. That is documented here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/release-health/status-windows-11-23h2#3351msgdesc&quot;&gt;https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/release-health/status-windows-11-23h2#3351msgdesc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a broken computer, you will see the following error message: Exception from HRESULT: 0x8002802B (TYPE_E_ELEMENTNOTFOUND)
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WSUS-API-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The documentation also explains how to resolve the issue using a KIR (known issue recovery), which requires some handwork or automation. To make this as easy as possible for users of &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt;, I added the installation of the KIR as part of the “BuiltIn: OS Install Windows Updates”. Finally, it downloads and installs the KIR package and activates it. A final reboot is needed to bring it to work. If you are using the script as part of the script collection (see image above), it will first patch the host and install updates on the second try of running the “BuiltIn: OS Install Windows Updates”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get the updated built-in scripts, you can click on the icon in the upper-right corner inside of the scripts page:
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WSUS-API-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you should have the updated script (reload the site first):
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WSUS-API-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, the Windows update procedure is working as expected:
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WSUS-API-04.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you want to adapt your scripts? Here is my implementation. Feel free to use it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Install Windows security updates directly over the internet. VM downloads the packages directly from Microsoft using the Windows Update service. A restart is required after the installation, which can be done with the script collection &amp;quot;OS Install Windows Updates&amp;quot;.
$updateCollection = New-Object -ComObject Microsoft.Update.UpdateColl
$updateSearcher = New-Object -ComObject Microsoft.Update.Searcher
$updateSession = New-Object -ComObject Microsoft.Update.Session

$updatesKb=&amp;quot;&amp;quot;

write-host(&amp;quot;Checking for updates&amp;quot;)
$result = $updateSearcher.Search(&amp;quot;IsInstalled=0 and Type=&apos;Software&apos; and IsHidden=0&amp;quot;)

if ($result.Updates.Count -EQ 0) {
	write-host(&amp;quot;No new updates found&amp;quot;)
}
else {
    try {
        $updateDownloader = $updateSession.CreateUpdateDownloader()
        $result.Updates|foreach {
            write-host(&amp;quot;Found: $($_.Title)&amp;quot;)
            $updatesKb=$updatesKb+$_.KBArticleIDs+&amp;quot; &amp;quot;
            $updateCollection.Add($_)|Out-Null
        }
        write-host(&amp;quot;Downloading updates&amp;quot;)
        $updateDownloader.Updates = $updateCollection
        $updateDownloads = $updateDownloader.Download()
        if (($updateDownloads.HResult -EQ 0) -AND ($updateDownloads.ResultCode -EQ 2)) {
            write-host(&amp;quot;Downloads success&amp;quot;)
        }
        else {
            write-host(&amp;quot;Downloads failed&amp;quot;)
            Write-host(&amp;quot;ScriptReturnMessage:{Download failed}:ScriptReturnMessage&amp;quot;)
            exit
        }
        write-host(&amp;quot;Installing updates&amp;quot;)
        $updateInstaller = New-Object -ComObject Microsoft.Update.Installer
        $updateInstaller.Updates = $updateCollection
        $updateDownloads = $updateInstaller.Install()

        write-host(&amp;quot;Applied updates: $updatesKb&amp;quot;)
    } catch {
        if (($_ -like &amp;quot;*0x8002802B*&amp;quot;) -and (Get-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Policies\Microsoft\FeatureManagement\Overrides&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;1931709068&amp;quot; -ErrorAction Ignore).&amp;quot;1931709068&amp;quot; -ne 0) {
            # Update API issue: https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/release-health/status-windows-11-23h2#3351msgdesc
            $hotFixKirUrl=&amp;quot;https://download.microsoft.com/download/3944f364-6483-49ab-af0d-3e2bd80dedaf/Windows%2011%2022H2%20KB5039302%20240711_20301%20Known%20Issue%20Rollback.msi&amp;quot;
            try {
                write-host (&amp;quot;Try to download KIR file to bring Windows Update API back&amp;quot;)
                (New-Object System.Net.WebClient).DownloadFile($hotFixKirUrl, &amp;quot;$env:temp\KIRKB5039302.msi&amp;quot;)
                Start-Process msiexec.exe -Wait -ArgumentList &apos;/I $env:temp\KIRKB5039302.msi /quiet&apos;
                if (-not (Test-Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Policies\Microsoft\FeatureManagement\Overrides&amp;quot;)) {
                    New-Item -Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Policies\Microsoft\FeatureManagement\Overrides&amp;quot; -Force -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
                }
                New-ItemProperty -Path &amp;quot;HKLM:\SYSTEM\CurrentControlSet\Policies\Microsoft\FeatureManagement\Overrides&amp;quot; -Name &amp;quot;1931709068&amp;quot; -Value 0 -Force -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
            } catch {
                write-host (&amp;quot;Your system is possible affected by a known issue regarding the Windows Update API. Installing a rollback was not possible due to an error: $_&amp;quot;)
                throw $_
            }
            # A reboot is required
            write-host(&amp;quot;Known issue recovery was applied to the system, but no updates. A restart is required before the next update will work. https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/release-health/status-windows-11-23h2#3351msgdesc&amp;quot;)
        } else {
            write-host (&amp;quot;The KIR installation is installed. If this is not working, another issue prevents the update process: $_&amp;quot;)
            throw $_
        }
    }
}

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Update-API-issue-0x8002802B_TYPE_E_ELEMENTNOTFOUND/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Update-API-issue-0x8002802B_TYPE_E_ELEMENTNOTFOUND/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>WVDAdmin - A native administration Gui for Azure Virtual Desktop (AVD) / Windows Virtual Desktop (WVD)</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;azure-windows-virtual-desktop-administration-with-wvdadmin&quot;&gt;Azure Windows Virtual Desktop administration with WVDAdmin&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azure (Windows) Virtual Desktop is generally available under continuous improvement and currently available in the ARM and in the Classic (Fall) version. The ARM version is completely into the Azure Portal.  Sometimes it helps to have a native GUI to make some configuration and - for me, most important - to have an easy image handling to deploy session hosts based on a template VM (golden image approach). Therefore I build a native Windows application to do this, and I’m happy to share it with the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in the new “Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop” solution to manage AVD even better with a lot of automation? &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Check it out here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 07/04/2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fH1_FzNyJf0&quot;&gt;Check out the Youtube video to install and configure WVDAdmin in four steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current version supports a lot of configuration and administration capabilities, and I’m continuously improving WVDAdmin. Some features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imaging
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create images from golden masters (without destroying the master)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handle sysprep and modern app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clean-up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of shared image gallery definitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollout
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollout of multiple session hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store some base settings encrypted for reuse (domain join name, password, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select VM type for each rollout (is not fixed to the host pool)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of ephemeral disks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support of a second partition from the master VM (D:)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Azure Monitor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AAD only, join to MEM/intune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AVD Support
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classic AVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARM AVD (Spring Update)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Migration of resources and session hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working with AVD resources
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add/create/delete
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host Pools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workspaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Session hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working with user sessions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disconnect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logoff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shadow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Session hosts
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move between host pools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start/Stop/Restart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete - with VM, disk, and nic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get error report from AVD agent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run scripts remotely on hosts (trigger Windows updates, enable RDP Shortpath, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change drain-mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change disk type, e.g.: on-start -&amp;gt; to Premium, after deallocation -&amp;gt; to HDD(for cost savings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove user assignment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual machine
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List all VMs with power state in all subscriptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start/Stop/Restart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run scripts remotely on hosts (trigger Windows updates, enable RDP Shortpath, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shrink disk to 64 or 32 GByte (to create small images for ephemeral hosts)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change disk type, e.g.: on-start -&amp;gt; to premium, after deallocation -&amp;gt; to HDD (for cost savings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create and restore snapshots with a click&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add an existing domain-joined VM as a session host&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-Tenant switch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split-Tenant mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for unused disks and nics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollout VM Scale Sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start and deallocate Scale Set instances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-image Scale Set instances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove customer-managed key (CMK)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;installation&quot;&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;release-history&quot;&gt;Release History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 07/04/2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fH1_FzNyJf0&quot;&gt;Check out the Youtube video to install and configure WVDAdmin in four steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;I&apos;m continuously updating WVDAdmin to make it easier to administrate and deploy WVD, users, and session hosts. Click to see the change history.&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Release&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Changes &amp;amp; Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9.08.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-08-23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Improvement of handling image gallery definitions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9.06.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-07-04&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Change of the API to get a registration token of a pool in response to Microsofts mail: “Update to Microsoft Desktop Virtualization API version 2023-09-05 by August 2, 2024, to avoid potential impact”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9.05.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-07-01&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Dls_v5 VM sizes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9.04.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-06-26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Issues while generating a host pool registration key is fixed&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9.03.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-05-13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: The prompt option while shadowing a user can be deactivated by setting the following reg-dword to 1: HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\MstscNoConsent (note: needs addition configurations on the hosts)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9.02.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-05-13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Issue in imaging script with Bitlocker disks in a few environments&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9.01.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-05-09&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Update: Imaging and rollout script to handle a sysprep auto-correction on Server OS&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.09.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2024-01-23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Rolling out the monitoring agent will accept any name of forwarding to log analytics in diagnostic settings of the host pool; Update of the imaging and rollout script&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.08.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-11-23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Update of the deployment and imaging script; Hibernation checkbox for rollout was hidden&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.07.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-11-15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for hibernation if available in the subscription&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.06.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-11-10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Windows 23H2; Fix: Failure during the copy of an image to an image gallery; Change: Update of the deployment and imaging script&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.05.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-10-13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for different VM sizes (Bas_v2, Bls_v2, Bats_v2, etc.); Update of the imaging script&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.01.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-09-19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support to capture trusted launch VMs directly into an Azure Compute Gallery; More reliable rollout of session hosts working around some of the AVD-agent issues&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.63.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-07-09&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Update of the installation script to install WinGet/Microsoft Package Manager applications&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.62.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-06-28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: New deployed hosts: In the first minutes, the correct start of the BootloaderAgent is monitored (if the service is not running, the service will be started)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.61.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-06-19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Modification to keep settings through Intune in the template&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.60.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-06-07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: In some cases a remote app icon crashed the application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.59.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-06&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Custom scirpt extension can ask for a parameter (see CustomScript-WithParameterString.ps1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.58.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-04-07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Ressetting the SCCM/MECM configuration during imaging; speed-up imaging for Windows 11 22H2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.57.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-04-03&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: A DLL was missing to read the Winget data (current packages)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.56.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-03-25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Update the imaging script to be even more resilient to sysprep issues. Sysprep is now monitored, and some workarounds for sysprep are triggered automatically in case of a sysprep error&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.55.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Deployment tags with an empty value are now set&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.54.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: If a larger disk size is used as the image: the last partition will be automatically extend; Add: Gallery images for Windows 10 22H2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.52.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Better handling for AAD only joined VM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.51.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Central India as meta-data location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.50.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Workaround to image Windows 11 22H2 (there is a bug in the sysprep process)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.49.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Secure boot enabled hosts are now supporting ‘Guest Attestation’ (automatically installed)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.48.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Support for Azure Disk Encryption fixed (ADE); Change to the PowerShell script: Avoiding a sysprep issue with the desired state configuration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.47.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: GUI, overlapping checkbox for use newes agent and secure boot&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.46.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Additional Galley images; Add: Download newest AVD agent during the rollout (instead of using the agent stored in the image)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.45.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Galley images are only shown if a custom image exist&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.44.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Australia East as meta-data location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.43.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for FX-series VM size&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.42.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can filter on the ‘Virtual Machines’ by the string ‘!orphanhosts’. That shows all VMs created by WVDAdmin or Hydra as a session host but currently not part of any seen host pool (used internally the tags WVD.Path or AVD.Path); Change: Modify WVD.Path/AVD.Path in another way while moving a session host to another host pool&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.41.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Japan East as meta-data location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.40.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Move host pool: The user assignment was not always kept;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.39.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can enable “Secure Boot” for marketplace images and for Custom Images in an Azure Compute Gallery (configure the VM image definition to support Secure Boot before copying a captured image to the gallery definition)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.38.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Deploy Azure market place images; Add: Show assigned users in the session hosts tab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.37.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Adding VM Size: NCasT4_v3-series; Add: All new created VMs are flagged to delete nic and disk if the VM is deleted in the Azure Portal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.35.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: NoTags-mode. Prevents WVDAdmin to set the default tags on new session hosts, scale sets and images. Set HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\NoTags to 1 (NoTags is REG_DWORD32)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.34.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Having custom script for imaging and deployment based on the tenant friendly name if running in the multi-AAD-tenancy mode &lt;a href=&quot;../Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Administration-for-CSP-and-Consulting-Partners&quot;&gt;Follow this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.33.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Dark-mode. Set HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\DarkMode to 1 (DarkMode is REG_DWORD32)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.32.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Using AAD-only expected the unnecessary field domain FQDN and the rollout button was greyed out in some situations&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.31.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for NVadsA10v5 VM types&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.30.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now deploy a host in a named availability zone (normally, the zone is (optional) automatically calculate to spread hosts around different zones&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.29.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: WVDAdmin stores the last rollout configuration and now (that is new), the last image, host pool, VM-size, storage type, etc.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.28.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Gettting the diagnostic setting on a host pool changed (updated API)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.25.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Configure diagnostic settings now enables all logs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.24.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can directly re-assign a user to a VDI session host or delete an assignment (on the session host tab change or delete the user asssignment)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.23.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: A new tab shows the name of the current background processes (Jobs)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.22.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: In some cases a VM-Scale-Set Instances where not shown and crashes the application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.21.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: VM Scale Set rollout issue&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.20.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Experimental support for building session hosts based on a secure boot Golden Master&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.19.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: VM sizes for D and E series V5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.18.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Change the VM size for multiple VMs (Azure -&amp;gt; Virtual Machines); New images are created with tags including the timestamp and resource ID of the master VM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.17.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: The API permission for Azure AD Graph is no longer needed for the service principal if you are using WVDAdmin for AVD (spring edition)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.16.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Session host rollout will set an additional tag to VM, Nic and Disk: WVD.Host=&lt;Name of session host&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.15.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: If you deallocate a VM without tags, the VM is deallocate but an error message is/was shown (Changing power state of Azure vm was not successful Object reference not set to an instance of an object.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.14.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Uninstallation of th RDAgent (if you capture a session host is now faster)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.13.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Join MEM/Intune while rolling out session hosts; Add: Function to shrink a disk of a VM to 32 GByte to rollout cheaper instances and/or use smaller instances with ephemeral disks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Optimization to capture a session host for a new image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.09.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Change the rollout process to be more reliable if you deploy a lot of hosts at once; Fix: Secrets can now have special characters&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.05.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: The windows can now be resized to full-screen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.01.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support to show subscription name in rollout and imaging tab (set HKEY_CURRENT_USER\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\ShowSubscriptionName to (reg-dword))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.00.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support to deploy AAD-only session hosts; Fix: Resize of V2 VM disks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin_1.6.99.0.msi&quot;&gt;1.6.99.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Meta-data location for Canada and the UK&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.98.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Resize the application window height in case you have a smaller resolution (&amp;lt;828 px)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.97.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Remove a Customer Managed Key (CMK) from a VM / Disk&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.96.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for the Edv4- and Edsv4-Serie&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.95.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now use CTRL+C in each table to copy the content of the selected column&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.94.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: An import of the registry settings failed if the windows decryption key is other than the user who exported the settings&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.92.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: A session host could be visible in the session host tab of anonter hostpool if the resource id of the host pools starts with the same string&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.91.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Create and restore snapshots of a VM (right click the VM in the Azure node)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.90.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Function to shrink a disk of a VM to 64 GByte to rollout cheaper instances and/or use smaller instances with ephemeral disks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.89.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Workaround to fix an issue in the Azure API querying VM. In subscriptions with a lot of VMs an error message could given back from the API which will be workaround with this version. Original error message from Azure: Resource provider ‘Microsoft.Compute’ failed to return collection response for type ‘virtualMachines’&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.88.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Option to rollout virtual machines based on an image without joining to WVD/AVD (for servers, new golden masters, …), Update: Newest PowerShell script for generalizing and deployment to 3.0: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/AutoUpdate/Scripts/ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&quot;&gt;ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.87.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Option to switch on “Power on connect” for pooled (and assigned) host pools (preview feature)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.86.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Option to directly roll-out new session hosts with actice Azure Disk Encryption (ADE) - See “secret features” below&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.83.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Update of ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1 - if you run it from a share with prepared MSIs, the MSIs are ignored and downloaded directly from Microsoft&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.82.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Script to enable screen capture protection per session host&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.81.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Localized time for the session list (WVD classic)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.80.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Message box before logging users off&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.79.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: VM list in the “Virtual Machines” node are now showing the private IP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.77.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Official support for meta-data regions: West Europe and North Europe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.76.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: New applications failed to create in an existing application group&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.75.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: In some cases session hosts are not displayed in the session hosts node (no matching resource id - upper-case / lower-case issue)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.73.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Automatically change the disk type on start/stop: Add a tag “&lt;a href=&quot;../Changing-the-disk-type-automatically-while-starting-or-deallocating-a-session-host,-VM-for-WVD&quot;&gt;WVD.AdvDiskType&lt;/a&gt;” to a VM with the value “StandardSSD_LRS” or “Premium_LRS”. On the stop, the disk is converted to HDD (lowes costs), and on start, the disk is converted to the named type.  Works only with WVDAdmin (not from the Azure Portal or scaling solutions)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.72.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Fix for a sysprep failure (Sysprep data was marked corrupt; cannot proceed) in the ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1 script; Add: Better handling for shutdown/start/delete VM tasks in the Virtual Machines node&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.71.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: The disk size for new session hosts can be selected (optional) to have a higher IOPS performance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.70.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: For preview only: Checkbox to enable upcoming “Start on connect feature”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.69.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Open files are not shown if different storage accounts in different subscriptions are used under some circumstances&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.68.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: West Europe as metadata location (can only be used if the subscription is in an appropriate preview program); Add: Some scroll bars to list boxes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.66.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Rollout from session hosts based on a share image gallery item failed in another subscription then the subscription containing the gallery image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.65.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Security query before hosts are started, stopped or restarted&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.64.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Install session host optionally with Azure Monitor Extension or sepago Azure Monitor (for Azure Monitor Extension: Make sure that you have configured the target host pool correctly once: Right-click -&amp;gt; Configure Diagnostic settings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.62.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now terminate file handles to an Azure Storage (orphaned handles avoiding a user to log in with its FSLogix profile) - Service Principal needs contributor permissions to the storage account&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.61.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: VC++ runtime if you use the destkop installer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.60.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Manage your Virtual Machines like session hosts: Click on Azure - Virtual Machines to list all VMs in your subscriptions (note: data for the VMs are are delayed (resource graph))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.59.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Rollback of advanced logging of create VM / create Image Powershell script: Shows unimportand messages as an error with existing images&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.57.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can enable diagnostic settings directly on a host pool, appgroup and workspace (right-click); Fix: Sometimes reading the state of a script extension is not directly possible. This cause that the WVDAdmin log shows an error even if everything works as expected&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.56.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Single session nodes are not listed under the session host node if more then 100 sessions exist to speed up WVDAdmin - all sessions are still in the session list&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.54.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Function to delete unused disks and nics; Add: More logging for the rollout of session hosts; Add: New VM-types, like L4s_v2, …&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.53.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Add session hosts automatically to Loadbalancer Backend Pools; Add: If a VM resource is unavailable, the first alternative VM size will be tried&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.51.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Custom script to install &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sepago.de/en/azure-monitor-en&quot;&gt;Azure Monitor for WVD from sepago&lt;/a&gt; to existing session hosts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.50.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Dhsv3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.46.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now rollout new session hosts with accelerated network configuration, Change: NICs are now created with the name of the VM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.45.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Add session hosts automatically to ASGs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin_1.6.42.msi&quot;&gt;1.6.42.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Dasv4-series&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.41.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Experimental feature: Add applications to session hosts from Windows Package Manager repository&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.40.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Having a script-path for building images is no longer needed. If you leave the text box empty, the local script coming with WVDAdmin will be used and directly send to the VM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.35.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: On a session host &amp;gt; State &amp;gt; Mouse over will show the health report of the host&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.34.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: The drop-down list “Feature release” was not shown correctly. Feature release is the selector between the different WVD/AVD versions like Fall (WVD classic) and Spring (WVD modern on ARM)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.32.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can run scripts on multiple classic session hosts: Win Updates: Install new available updates; Custom script: Custom script located in the program files folder of WVDAdmin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.30.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Sorting order for WVD/AVD resources&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.29.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Eav4 and Easv4-series&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.28.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Speed up adding a lot of VMs to the treeview&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.27.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for using availability zones. Select it from the drop-down list right to the resource group list&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.26.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can run scripts on multiple ARM session hosts: Win Updates: Install new available updates; Custom script: Custom script located in the program files folder of WVDAdmin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.24.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Multi selection and action on session hosts for ARM if you select a session host container; Fix: Scale Set instances wasn’t shown in 1.6.23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.23.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: New image was not visualized in the tree view after creation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.22.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for shared image galleries: Add a shared image gallery from the Azure Portal into a resource group managed by WVDAdmin. In WVDAdmin right-click an existing image and select “copy to shared image gallery”. An image can be rolled-out right clicking the shared image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.21.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Double-click on the tag Logs, Sessions or Sessions V2 enlarge the part of the windows (double-click again to revert)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.18.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: API change from Microsoft cause that updating a host pool property fails if the location is written like “Central US” (centralus is no problem); Add: First version able to deploy session hosts from images in a image gallery&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.16.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Session hosts icons  are now based on the availability state; Fix: Enumerating thousands of sessions with thousands of session hosts takes longer as expected (&amp;gt; 4 minutes)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.14.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support US Government Cloud. Activate: Add a new string Reg_SZ “Environment” with value “US” to HKCU\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.12.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for VM types: Dv4 and Dsv4-series, Ev4 and Esv4-series&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: WVD/AVD ARM resources are deployed with the tags; Workspaces and host pools are separated by subscription name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.9.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Generating toke for Spring host pool fails sometimes (Error: ExpirationTime value must be between one hour and 30 days from now”  - An error occurred while gathering an WVD2 token from backend: Object reference not set to an instance of an object.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.5.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for DD_v2 and DDS_V4 virtual machine types; Fix: Forwarding from the WVD/AVD API cause a authentication lost (error 401, 403 reading resources in the FALL update)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for GEN2 virtual machines&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.2.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: New naming feature for new session host. Default (is): Name for a session host is the highest matching name +1; new concept (must be enabled): Name for a session host is the next free name. To enable add a reg dword to HKCU\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin Name:NamingMode and value to “1”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Default session limit for V2 host pool is now 999999&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.0.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: The tag WVD.Path is aligned to Microsoft naming of “tenant” and “host pool” for the spring update. Tenant=resource group name and no longer subscription name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.9.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Load assigned users button to the app group tab (fall update)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.7.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can join existing VM’ to a host pool (VMs must be domain joined and not in a host pool right now)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.6.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now move session host around host pools not created with WVDAdmin (it downloads the necessary files automatically); you can join existing VM’ to a host pool (VMs must be domain joined)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.5.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Enumerating VMs was endless in some circumstance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Migration from Fall to Spring Update; moving session hosts to another host pool&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.3.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Improvement updating the treeview&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.0.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Spring-Update,-Spring-Release&quot;&gt;Supporting the WVD Spring Release / Spring Update&lt;/a&gt; ; Some user operations from the session grid are now async; Fix: Spontaneous resize of the windows if data are reloaded&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.9.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Filter users, session hosts and host pools in the overview of sessions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.8.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support to add users by groups from Azure Active Directory, including an AAD browser (check my &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Add-Users-and-Groups-to-WVD/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; and configure the service principal to use this feature)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.6.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: New VM sizes; all new scale sets are deployed as really scalable version (up to 600 instances each)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Service Principal Keys with some special characters are working now; Add: Faster loading of resources from WVD/AVD and Azure backend&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.2.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for NVv4 VM sizes (based on AMD Radeon Instinct  MI25-GPU); support to set custom Azure tags for resources while deploying resources&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.0.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: From an older version, disks are deployed as standard-hdd even if premium-disk was selected; Change: Connection views are now located parallel to the logging list on the bottom (tenant-view); Add: Function to check for an updated version via &lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin.xml&quot;&gt;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/WVDAdmin.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.6.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: New tag for session hosts: WVD.Path - used by &lt;a href=&quot;http://loganalytics.sepago.com/&quot;&gt;Azure Monitor for WVD&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/Project-MySmartScale&quot;&gt;Azure Autoscale for WVD - aka Project MySmartScale&lt;/a&gt; if an installed language pack conflicts with the Microsoft RDAgent (read this &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Language-Packs-Detecting-Host-Pool-and-Tenant-Name/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; to learn more)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.5.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Allow an local admin to shadow a user session (WVDAdmin needs direct access to the session host via RDP)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Networks are now listed as VNET/SUBNET in the rollout tab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.3.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for a special mode if your WVD/AVD tenant and the session hosts in two different Azure Active Directory tenants&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: WVDAdmin crashed if 1.3.0 is your first version of WVDAdmin (HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud doesn’t exist while checking for multi-tenancy mode)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.0.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: AAD multi-tenancy mode (drop down list to handle different AADs) - &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Administration-for-CSP-and-Consulting-Partners/&quot;&gt;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Administration-for-CSP-and-Consulting-Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.8.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: If you click a tenant a tenant wide list of sessions is listed.  Logoff or send messages to multiple sessions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.7.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: The main window of the application is now resizeable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.5.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Scale Sets (with normal and ephemeral disks) -&amp;gt; see below&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for availability sets&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.3.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for automatic and static assigned host pools&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;v121-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Fix: Logging of rollout parameter by Azure custom extension is removed to avoid logging secrets&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Rollout - OU can now be empty to join the default OU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Supporting “special license mode” to save up to 50% on compute-cost (&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/apply-windows-license&quot;&gt;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/apply-windows-license&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Template VM can now be a VM with a standard disk (non-managed)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: If you delete a VM the OS disk will deleted as well&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Support for ephemeral  disks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First published version - without auto-update of WVDAdmin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;configuration&quot;&gt;Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;service-principal-functional-account&quot;&gt;Service principal (functional account)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To work with the GUI, you need a service principal (function account) with permission to administrate access to the AVD and Azure resources. I decide to use a service principal to avoid confusion if my Azure AD user is only a guest account in the AVD tenant I have to administrate and easily switch between different tenants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a service principal, go to your Azure AD -&amp;gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.azure.com/#blade/Microsoft_AAD_IAM/ActiveDirectoryMenuBlade/RegisteredApps&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;App registration&lt;/a&gt; -&amp;gt; New registration and type a name for your principal like “ svc_WVDAdmin” and press “register”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-001.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on “certificates &amp;amp; secrets”. Click “new client secret”, select a validity period and a description (like “Key01”). Press “add”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-002.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-002&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copy the generated key directly - it will never be displayed again. Note the key for later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-003.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assign users to app groups, the service principal needs one API permissions to get the users and groups from Azure AD (optional):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the permission “Microsoft Graph” -&amp;gt; Application Permission -&amp;gt; Directory.Read.All&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/SP-PermissionToReadDirectoryObjects-01b.png&quot; alt=&quot;AADBrowser&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To consent, the permission and administrator of Azure AD have to grant this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/SP-PermissionToReadDirectoryObjects-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;AADBrowser&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to “Overview”. Note the “Application (client) ID” and the “Directory (tenant) ID” as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-004.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-004&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You now have all data for your service principal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tenant id&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service principal id (application id)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service principal key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;avd-permissions&quot;&gt;AVD permissions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter is for AVD ARM / Spring. &lt;a href=&quot;#azure-resource-permissions&quot;&gt;Skip&lt;/a&gt; this chapter if you only work with WVD Classic (Fall).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service principal needs permission to add and modify AVD resource objects (host pools, workspaces, app groups). To assign users and groups to app groups, the service principal needs the owner role on the resource groups you want to use for your AVD environment. Add the service principal in the next step and use the &lt;strong&gt;owner&lt;/strong&gt; role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;register-resource-provider&quot;&gt;Register Resource Provider&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have never worked with AVD, you have to register the AVD resource provider once. To do that, go to the Azure portal -&amp;gt; subscriptions -&amp;gt; select your subscription -&amp;gt; Resource providers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search for “Microsoft.DesktopVirtualization” and click on “Register”.
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-015.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-015&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;azure-resource-permissions&quot;&gt;Azure resource permissions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service principal needs permission to subscriptions or resource groups to manage your AVD resources, imaging template VM and rollout session hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open the Azure portal and go to the resource groups you want to use or to the subscriptions. In each resource group/subscription, click “Access control (IAM)” -&amp;gt; select “Add” -&amp;gt; Add role assignment. Select “owner” and search in “Select” for your service principal name. Click on the principal and save the settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Owner is needed to assign users to app groups. For other resources, “contributor” is fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-006.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-006&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service principal must have permissions to your virtual network (vnet) to assign new VMs to the right subnet. Go to your vnet, click “Access control (IAM)” -&amp;gt; select “Add” -&amp;gt; Add role assignment. Select “contributor” and search in “select” for your service principal name. Click the principal and save the settings. You could skip this step if you assigned the service principal to the subscription or to the resource group containing your vnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-007.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-007&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare-your-native-active-directory&quot;&gt;Prepare your “native” Active Directory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today each session host must be part of a “native” active directory domain (or have to use the domain services). To add new session hosts unattended, we need an administrative user account to add a computer object to the active directory domain. You can use an existing one, or you can create a new service user:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open “Active Directory Users and Computers” and create a user object with a complex password, and set a password to “never expire” (if you fine with this). I added the user &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:srv_WVD-Join@itprocloud.de&quot;&gt;srv_WVD-Join@itprocloud.de&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delegate permission for the user to an OU. I found a really good blog post from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/prajwaldesai&quot;&gt;Prajwal Desai&lt;/a&gt;. Check out hist post on (external web site): &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prajwaldesai.com/allow-domain-user-to-add-computer-to-domain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Method 2 – Delegate rights to user/group using Active Directory Users and Computers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case I added my function account to: “OU=WVD,OU=Azure,OU=Site,OU=Servers,OU=Sys,OU=Organisation,DC=ITProCloud,DC=test”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-create-a-file-share&quot;&gt;Optional: Create a file share&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In earlier versions (&amp;lt;1.6.40), you had to provide the deployment script and the AVD agent binaries on a custom file share or blob storage. With WVDAdmin 1.6.40 or newer, this no longer mandatory.
In some cases, where virtual machines don’t have access to the internet to download the AVD agent binaries, you can use a custom file share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Read more.&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hint: Alternatively, you can use Azure blob storage to store the script. Make the blob storage read-only and use the URL as rollout script-path. E.g.: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sharedservices01.blob.core.windows.net/wvd&quot;&gt;https://sharedservices01.blob.core.windows.net/wvd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a file share for the configuration script (which adds new session hosts to the domain and install the AVD agent). Give everyone at least read permissions. Set the NTFS permissions to everyone and read. This is necessary while during the first startup, the VM extension tries to execute the script. In this process, the file share is accessed anonymously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-009.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-009&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-010.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-010&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Place the following files in this share:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/AutoUpdate/Scripts/ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&quot;&gt;ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1&lt;/a&gt; (rename the download to .ps1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://query.prod.cms.rt.microsoft.com/cms/api/am/binary/RWrmXv&quot;&gt;Microsoft.RDInfra.RDAgent.msi&lt;/a&gt; (rename the file)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://query.prod.cms.rt.microsoft.com/cms/api/am/binary/RWrxrH&quot;&gt;Microsoft.RDInfra.RDAgentBootLoader.msi&lt;/a&gt; (rename the file)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure that you rename the files to fit the list above (without version numbers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-011.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-011&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important:&lt;/strong&gt; If you are using Windows Server &lt;strong&gt;2019&lt;/strong&gt; as file share, make sure that anonymous file share access is enabled. Create a GPO for the session hosts containing the following configurations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security Options:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accounts: Guest Account Status: Enabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network access: Let Everyone permissions apply to anonymous users: Enabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network access: Do not allow anonymous enumeration of SAM accounts and shares: Disabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;configure-wvdadmin&quot;&gt;Configure WVDAdmin&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please start WVDAdmin. Before you load AVD and Azure data, copy the Azure tenant id, service principal id, and service principal key into the welcome tab. Press save and load the data by clicking “Reload all”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are now able to administrate WVD, create images from template VMs and rollout new session hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time you want to roll out new session hosts, you have to enter some information from your Active Directory and file share configuration from above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-012.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-012&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local Admin and local pw. are the local administrator account credentials which you can enter at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-013.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-013&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;build-an-image&quot;&gt;Build an image&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can rollout VMs and VM Scale Set with images created by WVDAdmin. These images contain the logic to join the AD domain and WVD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can simple create an image from a template VM. The template VM must part of your AD like a standard client. You have not to sysprep or to normalize this template VM. Use the same template VM for Windows and application updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following these steps to build your template:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install a VM in the Azure portal. Select the right OS (like Windows 10 Enterprise for Virtual Desktops)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make all Windows updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join the VM to your AD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install your application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make your customizing (like installing language packages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shutdown the template VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create the image, open WVDAdmin and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigate to the Azure template VM (Azure -&amp;gt; Virtual Machines -&amp;gt; RG -&amp;gt; VM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-click -&amp;gt; “Create a template image”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the resource group to store the image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press “Capture”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can and should reuse the template VM for new updates and applications. After these changes, shut down the template VM and create a new image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;tipps-amp-tricks&quot;&gt;Tipps &amp;amp; Tricks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;vm-scale-sets&quot;&gt;VM Scale Sets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First node: VM Scale Sets cannot autoscale AVD session hosts. Auto-scaling only works for stateless services like a web server. But if you need hundreds of session hosts, then VM Scale Set allows you to work with these numbers efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Read more&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
From version 1.2.5, WVDAdmin support VM Scale Sets. A Scale Set can have several instances, which are the VMs / session hosts. There are some essential things you have to know if you use VM Scale Set with WVDAdmin and AVD itself:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a Scale Set with WVDAdmin. Select an image, right-click and select “Create session host from image”. Check “Rollout as VM Scale Set”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use regular disks and ephemeral disks. If you use ephemeral disks, you cannot deallocate the instances of your Scale Set. You have to delete the instances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today, you can not use ultra disks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can add and remove instances with WVDAdmin or in the Azure Portal. New instances will join the domain and WVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new instance can only join AVD if the session host with the new name doesn’t exist. If you delete instances, the session host entry will also be removed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can re-image single instances or all instances of a Scale Set. After that, the instances are “clean” as at the first rollout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding instances or re-imaging assumes that the Scale Set configuration (which is a custom script extension) has a valid AVD token to join new instances to WVD. While AVD provides only one token per host pool and that the token can be expiring, you can update the token with a right-click on the Scale Set and select “Update WVD token”. The max. lifetime of a token is 59 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unfortunately, WVDAdmin cannot change the source image for a VM Scale Set. So if you want to update the image for a host pool, take these steps:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollout a new Scale Set based on the new image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disable new logons for the old session host from the previous Scale Set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test the host pool based on the new Scale Set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If no user logged on to the ancient Scale Set, remove all instances from the Scale Set (this deletes the session hosts in AVD as well)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the Scale Set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ephemeral--disks&quot;&gt;Ephemeral  disks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ephemeral disks are awesome. They give you a high performance free of charge. Especially in a AVD multiuser environment where no data a stored permanently on the session hosts, this kind of disk can give you some value add.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Read more&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Ephemeral disks are running on the Azure hypervisor and not stored. This has some advantages:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no storage costs (!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A very high data throughput because the disks exist on the hypervisor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/michawets&quot;&gt;@MichaWets&lt;/a&gt;   blog post for more information:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloud-architect.be/2019/07/15/windows-virtual-desktop-running-on-ephemeral-os-disks/&quot;&gt;https://www.cloud-architect.be/2019/07/15/windows-virtual-desktop-running-on-ephemeral-os-disks/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can not deallocate a VM with this disk type - you have to delete the VM (and roll out a new one instead of starting a “normal” VM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not each VM size is available, and there are limitations of the disk size (image size for rollout) based on the VM size: Max ephemeral disk size for  Standard_D4s_v3  is 64 GByte while a  Standard_D8s_v3 can have up to 128 GByte. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-machines/linux/sizes-general&quot;&gt;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-machines/linux/sizes-general&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the Azure hypervisor fails, your session host will fail as well and can not be re-deployed automatically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-014.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;secret-features&quot;&gt;Secret Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WVDAdmin has some features not directly visible but configurable via registry keys. All settings in the registry are in the current user part under HKEY_CURRENT_USER\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin. Keep in mind to restart WVDAdmin after changing the registry settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Read more&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dark-mode&quot;&gt;Dark-mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From version 1.7.33 WVDAdmin can be run in dark-mode. Set the following reg value and restart WVDAdmin: HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\DarkMode to 1 (DarkMode is REG_DWORD32)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;multi-tenant-mode&quot;&gt;Multi-Tenant-Mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From version 1.3.0 WVDAdmin will support a multi-AAD-tenancy mode allowing to switch the Azure AD tenant very easily.
&lt;a href=&quot;../Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Administration-for-CSP-and-Consulting-Partners&quot;&gt;Follow this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;having-multiple-service-principals-for-a-single-tenant&quot;&gt;Having multiple Service Principals for a single Tenant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Multi-Tenant-Mode, you can add one service principal per tenant. Sometimes you need more service principals for the same tenant. You can add more service principals for a tenant if you append #1 directly behind the tenant id (or #2, …).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;naming-of-the-session-hosts&quot;&gt;Naming of the Session Hosts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you deploy session hosts to a host pool, WVDAdmin counts up the names from the highest available VM. E.g., if you have a session host with the name “WVD-PROD-012” and you rollout new hosts (WVD-PROD-###), the first new hostname is “WVD-PROD-013” - even if you have gaps in the existing numeration. You can force WVDAdmin to fill this gaps (non-existing hosts in the naming schema) if you set the following registry key:
Reg-DWord: &lt;strong&gt;NamingMode&lt;/strong&gt; = &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;split-tenant&quot;&gt;Split-Tenant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, the AVD tenant and the resources (sessions hosts) are in the same AAD tenant. If you have two Azure AD tenant, you can use WVDAdmin with a second service principal for the session hosts (resource tenant).
&lt;a href=&quot;../Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin-for-2-tenant-mode&quot;&gt;Follow this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;us-government-cloud&quot;&gt;US-Government Cloud&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WVDAdmin can be used to deploy AVD in the Azure Government Cloud. You can enable WVDAdmin to work in the US Government Cloud via registry:
Reg-SZ: &lt;strong&gt;Environment&lt;/strong&gt; = &lt;strong&gt;US&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-custom-actions-simultaneously&quot;&gt;Run custom actions simultaneously&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From version 1.6.15, WVDAdmin supports custom scripts to run administrative tasks simultaneously on different session hosts. And that is easy to use and to extend.
&lt;a href=&quot;../Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin-CustomScripts&quot;&gt;Follow this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;add-a-session-host-automatically-to-an-asg&quot;&gt;Add a session host automatically to an ASG&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add a session host automatically to application security groups (ASG) within the rollout process. To achieve this, add one or more tags to the host pool containing your new session hosts. Name &lt;strong&gt;WVD.Default.ASG.X&lt;/strong&gt; and add the azure resource id of an existing asg. X can be numbers to assign more ASGs. You can copy the id from an ASG from your browser. It looks like this: /subscriptions/&amp;lt;subscription-id&amp;gt;/resourcegroups/&amp;lt;resourcegroup-name&amp;gt;/providers/Microsoft.Network/applicationSecurityGroups/&amp;lt;asg-name&amp;gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/asg-001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tag for ASG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;add-a-session-host-automatically-to-a-loadbalancer-backend-pool&quot;&gt;Add a session host automatically to a Loadbalancer Backend Pool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add a session host automatically to a loadbalancer backend pool within the rollout process. To achieve this, add one or more tags to the host pool containing your new session hosts. Name &lt;strong&gt;WVD.Default.LBPool.X&lt;/strong&gt; and add the azure resource id of an existing loadbalancer backend pool. X can be numbers to assign more ASGs. You can copy the id from a pool from your browser. It looks like this: /subscriptions/&amp;lt;subscription-id&amp;gt;/resourcegroups/&amp;lt;resourcegroup-name&amp;gt;/providers/Microsoft.Network/loadBalancers/&amp;lt;loadbalancer-name&amp;gt;/backendAddressPools/&amp;lt;pool-name&amp;gt;
Keep in mind to use availability sets for each rollout to use this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rollout-session-hosts-with-azure-disk-encryption-ade&quot;&gt;Rollout session hosts with Azure Disk Encryption (ADE)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set two tags to the host pool to use it: “WVD.Default.KeyVault.Id” with the resource id of the KeyVault, “WVD.Default.KeyVault.KeyUri” with the URI (including the version) of the prepared key to wrap the secret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;create-an-image&quot;&gt;Create an Image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The image is not created. An error message occurs:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check if your template VM part of the AD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your file server Windows Server 2019, read above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check if you have set the NTFS and share permission correctly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Azure portal: Go to the temp VM (next to the template VM) and check the extension installation state. There should be an error message like script not found, access denied, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you renamed the RD agent and bootloader?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the script saved correctly: ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1, not ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t forget to delete the temp VM and temp disk to avoid costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure that your template VM uses managed disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The script generates additional log files in %WinDir%\System32\LogFiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Windows 7&lt;/em&gt;: Make sure to install PowerShell 5.1 and all Windows updates (including the optional updates without the language packages) to the template VM and restart the VM to take effect: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=54616&quot;&gt;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=54616&lt;/a&gt; Makes sure that you use the newest script file from 09/2020: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/AutoUpdate/Scripts/ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&quot;&gt;ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NEW: An endless loop of “Waiting for the temporary vm (power off)” : Update to the newest PowerShell script for generalizing: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/AutoUpdate/Scripts/ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&quot;&gt;ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;others&quot;&gt;Others&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have created a host pool, an app group, and assigned a user to the app group, but the user cannot see the apps/desktop.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For AVD ARM: Don’t forget to create a workspace and link the app group in the workspace. The workspace is mandatory to show the users’ resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the HTML5 web site: Check the correct web address:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARM/Spring: &lt;a href=&quot;https://aka.ms/wvdarmweb&quot;&gt;https://aka.ms/wvdarmweb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classic/Fall: &lt;a href=&quot;http://aka.ms/wvdweb&quot;&gt;http://aka.ms/wvdweb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 07/04/2024&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Common issues in Azure Virtual Desktop (VMs-Session Hosts relations)</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;vm--session-host-relation&quot;&gt;VM- Session Host relation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Azure Virtual Desktop, session hosts in host pools are providing remote applications or desktops to users. A session host is an object in a host pool. The session host is NOT the virtual machine (you can see in Azure in the Azure Virtual Machine view) but has a reference in a property to the virtual machine:
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Orphan-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session host (object) is relevant for Azure Virtual Desktop. And is reporting the “state” to the AVD backend. The important states for a session host are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Available (the session host is ready to accept connections)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unavailable (the session host is not ready and mostly off/deallocated)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shutdown (the session host is off/deallocated)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other, which are not relevant in this case&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AVD agents installed on the virtual machine report the state of the session host. So, the virtual machine is responsible for the state of the session host object in a pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;common-issues-in-this-relationship&quot;&gt;Common issues in this relationship&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the session host object and a virtual machine are independent resources and can have different problems, some behaviors must be monitored and mitigated if happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;orphan-virtual-machines&quot;&gt;Orphan Virtual Machines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a session host is deleted without the Virtual Machine, it will no longer appear in the AVD section in the Azure Portal and not in the session host list in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt;. That is expected. But while the virtual machine was not deleted, you are charged for additional costs – even if you are not using the virtual machine as a session host. The costs are higher if the virtual machine is still running and “invisible” from the AVD view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;unresponsive-avd-agents&quot;&gt;Unresponsive AVD Agents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, the AVD Agent (there are two involved services on each virtual machine) reports the state of a session host to the AVD backend. If the service cannot report the session host state to the AVD backend, the session hosts will stay in an “Unavailable” or “Shutdown” state.
From the AVD perspective, it looks like the session host is not running even if the virtual machine runs. That means that customers are charged for the virtual machine but don’t get a value from the AVD perspective (users cannot log in; hosts look like they were deallocated).
Possible causes of this issue:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A known issue is that the internal session host token expires after 90 days. So, if a session host is not running in 90 days to refresh the token, the host can no longer report the state to the AVD backend. &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.microsoft.com/azure/virtual-desktop/faq#how-often-should-i-turn-my-vms-on-to-prevent-registration-issues-&quot;&gt;https://learn.microsoft.com/azure/virtual-desktop/faq#how-often-should-i-turn-my-vms-on-to-prevent-registration-issues-&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The OS crashed inside of the VM. If the OS crashes inside of Windows and is not restarted automatically and starts well, the AVD agent is not started and cannot send the “state” to the AVD backend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The network is not working / cannot reach the AVD backend (Firewall): In this case, it’s technically not possible for the AVD Agent to report the state to the backend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The AVD agent failed to start. If the AVD Agent fails to start, it cannot update the state to the AVD backend. The reason for that must be found in the log files and the event log of the OS on the VM.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the network card or AVD services are disabled (which can be used to recreate this issue), the AVD agent cannot send the state to the AVD backend.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-orphan-resources&quot;&gt;Other orphan resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;orphan-disks&quot;&gt;Orphan disks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disks that are not assigned to a virtual machine. It still causes costs if forgotten to delete them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;orphan-network-interfaces&quot;&gt;Orphan network interfaces&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A network interface is not connected to a virtual machine or used as a private endpoint. They don’t cause costs, but they reserve one of the available IPs per card. If no IP is available for the next host/virtual machine, this can cause rollout issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;orphan-session-hosts&quot;&gt;Orphan session hosts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session hosts exist, but not the linked virtual machines. That doesn’t cause costs, but it can prevent autoscaling from working well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;actions-to-prevent-and-monitor-these-kinds-of-issues&quot;&gt;Actions to prevent and monitor these kinds of issues&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-the-avd-deep-insights-workbook&quot;&gt;Using the AVD Deep Insights workbook&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workbook &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Error-Drill-Down-Workbook/&quot;&gt;https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Error-Drill-Down-Workbook/&lt;/a&gt; is using the resource graph to show possible issues regarding both kinds of issues. In the section “Resources” are different types of possible issues are shown
Important: Some of the listed issues are expected during rollout, maintenance (Windows Update), imaging, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;orphan-virtual-machines-1&quot;&gt;Orphan virtual machines&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It shows virtual machines intended to be session hosts without a session host object. Only virtual machines with a tag with the name “AVD.Type” or “WVD.Type” and the value “SessionHost” are listed. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt; set the tag automatically with each deployment. Unfortunately, hosts deployed by the Azure Portal are not listed, but the tag can be set after or during a deployment from the portal.
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Orphan-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;unresponsive-avd-agents-1&quot;&gt;Unresponsive AVD agents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It shows the session hosts where the linked virtual machine is running, but the session host is in the state “unavailable” or “shutdown.” That is expected during a start/stop/rollout/delete of a session host but not during the normal runtime.
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Orphan-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-orphan-resources-1&quot;&gt;Other orphan resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The workbook also shows the following orphan resources:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orphan disks: Disks that are not assigned to a virtual machine. It still causes costs if forgotten to delete them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orphan network interfaces: Don’t cause costs but will reserve one of the available IPs per card. This can cause rollout issues if no IP is available for the next host/virtual machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orphan session hosts: The session hosts exist but not the linked virtual machines. That doesn’t cause costs, but it can prevent autoscaling from working well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;deployment-improvements-with-hydra-for-azure-virtual-desktop-and-wvdadmin&quot;&gt;Deployment improvements with Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop and WVDAdmin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both tools can be used to easily deploy new session hosts. The newest versions install some scheduled tasks on the newly deployed session hosts / virtual machines to monitor the start-up of the AVD services. E.g., if a start of one service fails (AVD agent bootloader) in the first minutes after a start, the task will start the service again. That can help if the service is not running in an issue again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-hydra-for-azure-virtual-desktop&quot;&gt;Using Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;failed-start-of-session-hosts-unresponsive-avd-agent&quot;&gt;Failed start of session hosts (unresponsive AVD agent)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start process of a session host is monitored If it is started with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt; (in the Hydra portal or by autoscaling). If a session host is not changing the state to “available” or “updating” in 10 minutes, the host will be marked as “critically failed”. This is visible on the dashboard and in the session host list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notification on the dashboard:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Orphan-04.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notification in the session host list:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Orphan-05.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: If a host is started outside of Hydra—in the Azure Portal or with the Start VM on connect feature—Hydra cannot mark it.
Tip: While Hydra’s logging data are stored in Log Analytics, it is possible to create an alert to be notified by mail or to open a ticket via REST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;notification-of-orphan-vms-and-unresponsive-avd-agents&quot;&gt;Notification of orphan VMs and unresponsive AVD agents&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From version 1.0.7.4, Hydra will show a notification if orphan hosts or unresponsive AVD agents are detected:
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Orphan-06.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The detection runs every 20 minutes, and resources seen three times in a row with the same possible issue are shown. So, the first notification is shown after one hour (to be changed). That should prevent the falsest alerts while such a state is possible during deployments, starts, stops, deletes, imaging, or if the service account does not have permission to see all needed resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-orphan-resources&quot;&gt;Further orphan resources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Orphan disks and network interfaces will be listed (like virtual machines) in the near future in Azure Resources -&amp;gt; Orphan Resources in Hydra soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-stepsf&quot;&gt;Next stepsf&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an upcoming version, the hosts and VMs will be directly visible in the Hydra portal, including the possibility of taking some actions (like deleting resources, reinstalling the AVD agent, etc.).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like any other IT solution, Azure Virtual Desktop may have issues. Therefore, it is important to monitor and take action to avoid additional costs without gaining value from the AVD perspective.
I personally use the tools I built to deploy hosts more reliably and to get notified about possible issues. And: &lt;strong&gt;It always makes sense to monitor the cost and cost prediction of subscriptions in Azure.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Common-Issues-Orphan-Resources-unresponding-AVD-Agent/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Common-Issues-Orphan-Resources-unresponding-AVD-Agent/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Debugging Azure Virtual Desktop errors/issues/network latency and bandwidth with an interactive Workbook</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Correctly configured, Azure Virtual Desktop sends diagnostic data to a log analytics workspace (Azure Monitor). There are several logs containing data about the events in the backend:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Log Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDAgentHealthStatus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Details about the session hosts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDConnections&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;All about connections from a user to a session host&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDErrors&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Error message from different sources (client, RDGateway, Loadbalancer, …)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDFeeds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Log about clients downloading information about the AVD resources&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDHostRegistrations&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Logs if a host tries to register to a host pool&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDManagement&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Log about administrative tasks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDCheckpoints&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Detailed information related to logins, errors, …&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDConnectionNetworkData&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Network information (bandwidth and RTT)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get the logs, configure at least the host pool to send log information to a log analytics workspace. You can do this on a host pool level -&amp;gt; Diagnostic settings -&amp;gt; Add diagnostic settings -&amp;gt; Select all Logs and target a log analytics workspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Avd-Error-Monitoring-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt; to do that (use version 1.7.25 or higher):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Avd-Error-Monitoring-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will take a while before you can see the first data. The data can be queried with the KUSTO language or analyzed with custom workbooks. I prepared a workbook to dig into the data. Most visualizations are interactive. So you can drill down by selecting users, networks, agent versions, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/AVD-Monitoring-Workbook-Errors.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/MonitorSessionHosts-12.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Avd-Error-Monitoring-13.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Avd-Error-Monitoring-14.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can install the workbook directly as a template into your subscription: &lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.azure.com/#create/Microsoft.Template/uri/https%3A%2F%2Fblog.itprocloud.de%2Fassets%2Ffiles%2FAzureDeployments%2FWorkbook-AVD-Error-Logging.json&quot;&gt;Install the workbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while, the workbook is visible as a new template in: &lt;strong&gt;Log Analytics -&amp;gt; Workbooks -&amp;gt; Azure Virtual Desktop -&amp;gt; AVD - Deep-Insights&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can select the time frame and host pool from the drop-down list. The other drop-down lists are optional. Please ensure that you have included the essential errors from the error selector. Remember that not all errors are making issues (e.g., “&lt;em&gt;ConnectionFailedClientDisconnected&lt;/em&gt;” occurs if a session goes in the disconnected mode while the users close its notebook).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please let me know if you have ideas to extend the workbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Version&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;01/28/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Initial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/17/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Include RTT and bandwidth (right now, host pool must be in the validation environment and diagnostic data must include &lt;strong&gt;NetworkData&lt;/strong&gt;); see &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-virtual-desktop/collect-and-query-network-data-for-azure-virtual-desktop/m-p/3140397&quot;&gt;https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-virtual-desktop/collect-and-query-network-data-for-azure-virtual-desktop/m-p/3140397&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Name changed to AVD - Deep-Insights&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/16/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Include Logon timing (GPO, FSLogix, Authentication, etc.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;04/14/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In Session Bandwidths &amp;amp; Latencies: The connection type is shown if RDP Short Path is used (Public, Private). See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/shortpath-public&quot;&gt;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/shortpath-public&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;05/03/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;New visualization: Logon timing per day and category over the time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/11/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;New visualization: Connections over time, unhealthy session hosts, graphic performance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/03/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Optimization for charts to show data over a large time frame&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/14/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A new tab “Resources”, to show orphan session hosts; Fix: Number of active and inactive sessions - timeselector was not correct&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/18/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A new tab “Resources”, to show orphan VMs (where the session host object is missing)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/01/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Changed the description for the estimated available bandwidth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/09/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Added orphan disks and orphan nics to the “Resources” tab (note: All orphand devices will also shown and could be removed in Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop, version 1.0.1.84 (comming soon))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/02/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Added “Water Markings” to query session information by the feature &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/watermarking&quot;&gt;WaterMarking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/20/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Added “Unresponding AVD Agents” in the tab “Resources” to identify running VM with a non responding AVD agent&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/21/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Added new tab “FSLogix” to show the size, usage and free space of the FSLogix profiles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/08/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix in the time selector; allow to selecte multiple host pools; show active sessions with user name and started desktop/remote app&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/31/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Show office container size and usage (ODFC) in the FSLogix tab (additional to the profile container)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;07/01/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix/Workaround: VHDFreeSpace is stored as text in MByte and not in GByte if the value is less then 1 GByte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/13/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Show the last heart beat time in the Orphan session hosts view and warns, if the heart beat is longer then 90 days ago&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;3.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;06/24/2024&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Orphan resources are now including temporary orphan hosts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.azure.com/#create/Microsoft.Template/uri/https%3A%2F%2Fblog.itprocloud.de%2Fassets%2Ffiles%2FAzureDeployments%2FWorkbook-AVD-Error-Logging.json&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aka.ms/deploytoazurebutton&quot; alt=&quot;Deploy to Azure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please click twice on create to accept the Microsoft Agreement of terms - Workbooks don’t generate costs&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Error-Drill-Down-Workbook/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Error-Drill-Down-Workbook/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Monitor</category>
        
        <category>Log Analytics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to image a Confidential Golden Master VM and deploy confidential Session Hosts for Azure Virtual Desktop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Azure confidential VMs offer strong security and confidentiality for customers by isolating data. That can also make sene for Azure Virtual Desktop. One of my favorite deployment methods is the Golden Master apporach with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt;. Hydra allows image creation without losing the Golden Master. So, a Golden Master can be updated and imaged unlimitedly. Tip: Imaging, including patching, can be automated and scheduled with Hydra.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: Hydra version 1.0.7.3 or newer is needed for confidential support. To update Hydra: Click on the avatar (roboter icon) in the upper right corner and select: “Update Engine”. After a while, reload the Hydra Portal website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we create a Golden Master:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a Golden Master. Ensure that you create the Golden Master as a Confidential VM. Select a confidential VM size and security type &lt;strong&gt;Confidential virtual machines&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Confidential-Imaging-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
To encrypt also the OS disk, select &lt;strong&gt;Confidential OS disk encryption&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Confidential-Imaging-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Configure the other settings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install all applications and updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do some configurations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confidential images can only be stored in specific Azure compute gallery definitions. Create a new gallery definition for confidential VM:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use an existing compute gallery or create a new compute gallery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on Add -&amp;gt; VM image definition
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Confidential-Imaging-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The security type must be &lt;strong&gt;Confidential&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Confidential-Imaging-04.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter a name and fill out the fields Publisher, Offer, and SKU (the combination of publisher, offer, and SKU must be unique in the gallery)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on review and create to create the gallery definition
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Confidential-Imaging-05.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create an image, go to your Hydra installation and open Image Builder -&amp;gt; Create an image&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select your confidential Golden Master from the virtual machine list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the resource group of the Golden Master VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the compute gallery definition in the Azure Compute Gallery section&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure the locations where the image should be available&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on Create Image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Confidential-Imaging-06.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Important: The golden master &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; also be a confidential VM. The encryption configuration of the OS disk is also stored and will be used by rolling out session hosts based on that image.
Hint: If the OS disk is encrypted, the imaging process will take longer. A clone is created during the imaging (and later deleted), and the disk is decrypted. This will take a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After an image is created, we can configure the rollout configuration of our confidential host pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Hydra: Dashboard -&amp;gt; Your host pool -&amp;gt; Configuration -&amp;gt; New Session Host Rollout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure all settings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select a  confidential virtual machine size (type confidential in the field to show the sizes):
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Confidential-Imaging-07.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the session host list of the pool, click on the plus icon to deploy confidential hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hint: There is another option for non-trusted-launch VMs: This kind of VM-images can be stored to a &lt;strong&gt;Confidential Supported&lt;/strong&gt; gallery definition with Hydra. Finally, you can create new hosts based on that Confidential suported Gallery Definition Versions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Capturing-and-Deploying-Confidential-Session-Hosts/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Capturing-and-Deploying-Confidential-Session-Hosts/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to image a Golden Master VM based on a plan to a compute gallery definition</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Azure Marketplace offers many preconfigured VMs, which are preconfigured images from a third-party vendor used to deploy a VM. One popular offering is “CIS Hardened Image Level 1 on Microsoft Windows 11 Enterprise—Gen 2.” The Center for Internet Security Inc. has hardened the Windows 11 image and provides it through the marketplace for a small fee. That is called a “Plan” for a VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That image can be used for a Golden Master: Install your application on top, create an image, and deploy multiple session hosts / virtual machines in your Azure Virtual Desktop environment (and yes, that also costs a bit more for each deployed host). Unfortunately, it’s not so easy to capture an image directly into an Azure Compute Gallery definition - which is needed if you want to deploy trusted launch VMs afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When attempting to capture an image directly into a Compute Gallery Definition using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt; (to create loss-less images), you may encounter the following error message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The resource with id ‘/subscriptions/xxxxxxxxxxx/resourceGroups/WVD_Templates/providers/Microsoft.Compute/virtualMachines/TEMP_T-CIS-Plan-01_2024-06-19_19-19-51’ has a different plan [’{“name”:“cis-windows11-enterprise-l1-gen2”,“publisher”:“center-for-internet-security-inc”,“product”:“cis-windows-enterprise”,“promotionCode”:null}’] than the parent gallery image plan [‘null’]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The error message gives a hint. The Compute Gallery Definition must be prepared to accept image versions with a plan (the market place image). Therefore, we have to create a matching Compute Gallery Definition. But first, we have to figure out the “Purchase plan name”, “Purchase plan publisher name”, and “Purchase plan product name”. If you already have deployed the VM / your Golden Master. You can grab the information form the JSON-view of the VM:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Gallery-Plan-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, we will use the following data to configure the Compute Gallery Definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Name = Purchase plan name: cis-windows11-enterprise-l1-gen2&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Publisher = Purchase plan publisher name: center-for-internet-security-inc&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Product = Purchase plan product name: cis-windows-enterprise&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, we can start creating the Compute Gallery Definition. If you don’t already have a Compute Gallery, create it first. Click on Add -&amp;gt; VM image definition. Fill out the formula, e.g.:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VM image definition name: &lt;strong&gt;Custom-CIS-Image_TrustedLaunch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security type: &lt;strong&gt;Trusted launch&lt;/strong&gt; (not support); that allows you to create trusted launch enabled hosts later&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publisher: &lt;strong&gt;ITProCloud&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer: &lt;strong&gt;CIS-Image-Custom-TrustedLaunch&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SKU: &lt;strong&gt;A&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(The combination of Publisher/Offer/SKU must be unique in a Compute Gallery)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Gallery-Plan-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NEXT -&amp;gt; NEXT -&amp;gt; Publishing options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That page is important for the plan configuration to store the CIS image. Fill out the fields for “Purchase plan name”, “Purchase plan publisher name”, and “Purchase plan product name” with the noted values:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Gallery-Plan-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click Review + Create -&amp;gt; Create&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Gallery-Plan-04.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you can create a loss-less image with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt; directly into the Gallery Definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Gallery-Plan-05.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-How-to-image-a-Golden-Master-VM-based-on-a-plan-to-a-compute-gallery-definition/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-How-to-image-a-Golden-Master-VM-based-on-a-plan-to-a-compute-gallery-definition/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Imaging, Rollout and Manage Azure Virtual Desktop on Azure Stack HCI with Hydra</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;manage-azure-virtual-desktop-on-azure-stack-hci-with-a-hrefhttpsgithubcommarcelmeurerwvd-hydrahydraa&quot;&gt;Manage Azure Virtual Desktop on Azure Stack HCI with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt; is the one-stop solution for managing and operating AVD in a clever and easy way. Hydra supports administrators in managing user sessions, creating images without losing the Golden Master, deploying and re-deploying session hosts, and automating daily tasks with a powerful and easy-to-use engine. This and much more for single and multiple tenants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, starting from version 1.0.6, Hydra supports hosts on &lt;strong&gt;Azure Stack HCI 23H2&lt;/strong&gt;. Does mean you can leverage the feature set of Hydra to handle hosts on HCI in mostly the same way as hosts in Azure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Autoscaling of pooled and personal host pools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let user start their personal hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create images from Azure VMs and store them in a custom location (on HCI)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create multiple hosts with a click&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace hosts with hosts based on an updated image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automat the daily tasks with scripts and collections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handle user sessions independently from the host type (HCI vs. Azure VM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the Hydra agent to show and terminate processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autoscaling is especially important, while Microsoft announced &lt;strong&gt;charging 1 US cent per core and hour&lt;/strong&gt; for a running host on HCI. Additionally, the self-service for users of personal hosts is nice as well, while power-on-connect is not available for HCI right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-does-hydra-integrate-hosts-on-hci&quot;&gt;How does Hydra integrate hosts on HCI&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no need for a special configuration. If Hydra reads a custom location in Azure, it automatically offers the networks in the location as a target to roll out new hosts. Existing hosts on HCI are also automatically handled by Hydra. The only &lt;strong&gt;requirement is Azure Stack HCI 22H3&lt;/strong&gt; with a configured resource bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is nearly no difference between hosts in Azure or on HCI for Hydra. Theoretically, a host pool can contain both types of hosts (if it makes sense). The difference between both types of hosts is the location/custom location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, some configurations are unavailable for HCI hosts, like switching the disk types.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-configure-autoscaling&quot;&gt;How to configure autoscaling&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autoscaling works in the same way as hosts in Azure. Follow the documentation to configure autoscaling: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra?tab=readme-ov-file#scaling&quot;&gt;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra?tab=readme-ov-file#scaling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As shown in the screenshot, Hydra starts session hosts automatically before users try to log in. And in the other direction, if users are logging off at the end of the work day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/HCI-Hydra-002.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that Power-On-Connect is not working for HCI right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-give-users-access-to-start-their-personal-hosts&quot;&gt;How to give users access to start their personal hosts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Give users or a user group the role “User” in Hydra. After this, users can access Hydra and only see the menu item “My Sessions &amp;amp; Hosts”. From this, users can start/stop/restart the personal hosts or log off their sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/HCI-Hydra-006.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-to-create-a-custom-image-and-do-a-roll-out&quot;&gt;How to create a custom image and do a roll out&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating images based on a “Golden Master” is one of the strengths of Hydra. Compared to a manual approach, Hydra always runs the imaging process of a clone of the Golden Master. This is important to avoid that sysprep destroying the Golden Master. So, with Hydra, administrators can use the original Golden Master to update and maintain the image the next time. The imaging process looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/HCI-Hydra-003.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After creating the image, the clone is deleted during the clean-up.
Imaging for HCI works in the same way, but we must consider a few points right now:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can only use an Azure VM as a master – not a VM on HCI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While we cannot use Trusted Launch for custom images in HCI, our Golden Master must have the &lt;strong&gt;security type “Standard”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can create a custom image for HCI with the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create your Golden Master VM in Azure (not HCI)
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use a Windows 11 (multi-user) marketplace image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security type: &lt;strong&gt;Standard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Login to the VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optionally: Join to an AD domain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Windows Updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install Applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the Hydra portal -&amp;gt; Image Builder -&amp;gt; Create an Image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select your Golden Master VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select a Target Resource Group to store the Azure image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the section “Azure Stack HCI” select the custom location&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optionally configure the other two options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on “Create Image”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caution:&lt;/strong&gt; Never let Hydra delete an image that is being used by a virtual machine. VMs can no longer be started or stopped if the base image is deleted. Only deletion would work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/HCI-Hydra-004.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The VM will be cloned, and the image will be transferred to the custom location (that could take a while). After that, you can create new hosts in a host pool by configuring the rollout configuration in the Hydra settings “New Session Host Rollout” of the host pool:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/HCI-Hydra-005.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on the plus icon in the session host list of a host pool to roll out hosts with the custom image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-hrefhttpsyoutubeji6plhjvcysee-a-short-video-on-how-to-work-with-hydra-and-azure-stack-hcia&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ji6_pLhJVCY&quot;&gt;See a short video on how to work with Hydra and Azure Stack HCI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Hydra-For-Azure-Stack-HCI-Deplyoment-Management/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Hydra-For-Azure-Stack-HCI-Deplyoment-Management/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Stack HCI</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
