<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ITProCloud Blog</title>
    <description>Welcome to my blog. I'm writing this blog to share my experiences mainly in IT focused on Microsoft Azure. The blog is part of the ITProCloud GmbH.</description>
    <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://blog.itprocloud.de/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 19:41:25 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 19:41:25 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to get the Client IP Address in Azure Virtual Desktop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While migrating Virtual Desktop Environments to AVD, I got another challenge from the past: Sometimes, companies use the client IP address to identify the user’s location to map a specific printer in the location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, AVD didn’t provide this client’s IP address. Even the property of &lt;em&gt;WTSQuerySessionInformation&lt;/em&gt; is empty. I only get the internet-faced IP address if I try to use the diagnostic settings. But not the client’s own address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is a solution/workaround: If clients are using RDP Shortpath (public or private), we can grab the information locally to do some printer mappings. The good thing is that RDP Shortpath is enabled by default (except for the HTML 5 web client).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RDAgent, installed on each session host, reports a lot of data to the backend (logs). You can configure the diagnostic settings to store this data to log analytics or some other data stores. Some of those logs are also on the session host in the event log.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event log &lt;strong&gt;“RemoteDesktopServices”&lt;/strong&gt; contains the log entries. The source &lt;strong&gt;“Microsoft.RDInfra.Diagnostics.DataSink.RestPipelineSink”&lt;/strong&gt; contains data about RDP Shortpath connection, including the IP address of the client:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use the activity ID to match the information to a specific user on the host. The correlation user/activity ID is stored in the log from the source “Microsoft.RDInfra.RDAgent.ConnectionTrackingService.DefaultConnectionTrackingService”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built a small tool to read the event log continuously. AvdClientIp reads the single entries, extracts the data, and matches the data by the activity ID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The installation of AvdClientIp will create a scheduled task with the name “ITPC-AVD-ClientIP”. This task starts with the computer and monitors the RemoteDesktopServices event log. If a client IP is detected, the tool writes the client IP into the users’ registry in &lt;strong&gt;HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Volatile Environment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ClientIpValue		-&amp;gt; IPv4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ClientIpUTC		-&amp;gt; The timestamp&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/AVD-Client-IP-00.png&quot; alt=&quot;AADBrowser&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;logging-and-configuration&quot;&gt;Logging and configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default configuration can be changed by setting the following values to the registry HKLM:\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\AvdClientIp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Default value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;HideUserNamesInLogfile&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reg_DWORD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hides the user names in the logfile&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0=false&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Logging&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reg_DWORD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Enbale logging&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1=true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
AvdClientIp writes a log file to *%AppData%\ITProCloud\AvdClientIp.log. *
&lt;p&gt;Note: It would be much better if the RDAgent would store this information directly in the registry or provide the information with the WTSQuerySessionInformation. So, use this tool as a workaround until we get the data natively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;note&quot;&gt;Note&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be much better if the RDAgent would store this information directly in the registry or provide the information with the WTSQuerySessionInformation. So, use this tool as a workaround until we get the data natively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;kudos&quot;&gt;Kudos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big thank to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/j%C3%B6rg-hoffmann-078b3523/&quot;&gt;Jörg Hoffmann&lt;/a&gt; finding the right logs 👍&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;download&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/AvdClientIp.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 10/23/2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to send me ideas for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Client-IP/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Client-IP/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>OneDrive Clean-Up for Azure Virtual Desktop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Running OneDrive with Azure Virtual Desktop is a common scenario and enables users to work in a modern way with Teams and SharePoint. If FSLogix is used, there is a challenge in combination with OneDrive: Users can download OneDrive files to the host, and the data are stored in the profile. The profile size increases heavily and causes some extra costs on the storage account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having so many OneDrive files stored in the profile may make no sense in every case - if a user access a file, the file is downloaded automatically (on demand). And it’s mostly fine to “unpin” the file later if the file is no longer needed. The files are downloaded fast, while AVD and OneDrive are in the Microsoft cloud.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OneDrive files can have three different states:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud:&lt;/strong&gt;
The file content is in the cloud only. The file system simulates that the file exists. While the content is not on the disk, the files don’t need storage on the device. If a user opens such a file, the content is downloaded, and the file state change to On-Device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On-Device:&lt;/strong&gt;
The file content is also on the local disk, and the files are using local storage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always:&lt;/strong&gt;
The file content is also on the local disk, and the files are using local storage. OneDrive wouldn’t change the state to “Cloud”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ODClaenUp-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OneDrive can change the state to “Cloud” on normal Windows 10/11 devices using storage sense. Based on the implementation of storage sense, this is not working for Azure Virtual Desktop (Multi-Session) with FSLogix profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A solution to avoid profile blotting in combination with FSLogix is changing the state of OneDrive files to “Cloud” (unpin files). If files are unpinned, they are no longer using local storage, and the “Disk Compaction” of FSLogix would reduce the profile automatically over time (or have more space left for user data).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built a small tool to solve this challenge (I didn’t find a native solution). The tool is called OneDrive CleanUp. OneDrive CleanUp can run in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started automatically with the login of the user (after the installation, it creates a link in the start-up folder of the start menu). It directly starts in the background and validates and maybe unpin OneDrive files. This process is repeated every 30 minutes and during the logoff of the user.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start the program with the parameter /RunOnce during the logoff using a (group) policy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I prefer the first method to ensure that OneDrive has time to react to the unpinning of files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example for method 2:
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ODClaenUp-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;result&quot;&gt;Result&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my test, my profile grew to 8 GByte while I pinned some files in OneDrive, and after logoff, the profile went back to 800 MByte while the tool unpinned the OneDrive files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;logging-and-configuration&quot;&gt;Logging and configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default configuration can be changed by setting the following values to the registry HKLM:\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\OneDriveCleanUp&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Default value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Enabled&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reg_DWORD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If false, the application will not check the files&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1=true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RunEachMinutes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reg_DWORD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Check OneDrive files each minutes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AlwaysUnpinFilesOlderThenDays&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reg_DWORD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Unpin files older then days (0: disabled )&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;AllowMbytesOnDisk&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reg_DWORD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Allow the configured value in MByte on the local disk&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;5120&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;IgnoreFilesContaining&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Reg_SZ&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;String with separated values (;). If the path of a file contains one of the values, the file is ignored&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Empty&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
OneDrive CleanUp writes a log file to %AppData%\ITProCloud\OneDriveCleanUp.log. 
&lt;p&gt;Example:
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/ODClaenUp-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-does-it-work&quot;&gt;How does it work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OneDrive CleanUp regularly checks all OneDrive paths and calculates the size of the disk. If the size is larger than the configured maximum size (AllowMbytesOnDisk), it unpins files to go under the configured size. It starts from the oldest to the newest file based on the LastAccessTime property.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;release-notes&quot;&gt;Release notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Release&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Changes &amp;amp; Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-04&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Initial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-07-13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Files larger than 2 GByte were counted wrong&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-10-17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Files larger than 4 GByte were counted wrong&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;download&quot;&gt;Download&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/OneDriveCleanUp.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 10/17/2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to send me ideas for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 17 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/OneDrive-Clean-Up-For-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-AVD-agains-Profile-Blotting-Copy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/OneDrive-Clean-Up-For-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-AVD-agains-Profile-Blotting-Copy/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>WVDAdmin - A native administration Gui for Azure Virtual Desktop (AVD) / Windows Virtual Desktop (WVD)</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;azure-windows-virtual-desktop-administration-with-wvdadmin&quot;&gt;Azure Windows Virtual Desktop administration with WVDAdmin&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azure (Windows) Virtual Desktop is generally available under continuous improvement and currently available in the ARM and in the Classic (Fall) version. The ARM version is completely into the Azure Portal.  Sometimes it helps to have a native GUI to make some configuration and - for me, most important - to have an easy image handling to deploy session hosts based on a template VM (golden image approach). Therefore I build a native Windows application to do this, and I’m happy to share it with the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you interested in the new “Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop” solution to manage AVD even better with a lot of automation? &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Check it out here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 10/13/2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fH1_FzNyJf0&quot;&gt;Check out the Youtube video to install and configure WVDAdmin in four steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current version supports a lot of configuration and administration capabilities, and I’m continuously improving WVDAdmin. Some features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Imaging
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create images from golden masters (without destroying the master)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Handle sysprep and modern app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clean-up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of shared image gallery definitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollout
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollout of multiple session hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Store some base settings encrypted for reuse (domain join name, password, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select VM type for each rollout (is not fixed to the host pool)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of ephemeral disks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support of a second partition from the master VM (D:)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Azure Monitor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AAD only, join to MEM/intune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AVD Support
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classic AVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARM AVD (Spring Update)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Migration of resources and session hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working with AVD resources
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add/create/delete
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Host Pools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Application groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Workspaces&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Session hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Working with user sessions
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disconnect&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Logoff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send message&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shadow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Session hosts
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move between host pools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start/Stop/Restart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Delete - with VM, disk, and nic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get error report from AVD agent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run scripts remotely on hosts (trigger Windows updates, enable RDP Shortpath, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change drain-mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change disk type, e.g.: on-start -&amp;gt; to Premium, after deallocation -&amp;gt; to HDD(for cost savings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove user assignment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Virtual machine
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List all VMs with power state in all subscriptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start/Stop/Restart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run scripts remotely on hosts (trigger Windows updates, enable RDP Shortpath, …)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shrink disk to 64 or 32 GByte (to create small images for ephemeral hosts)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change disk type, e.g.: on-start -&amp;gt; to premium, after deallocation -&amp;gt; to HDD (for cost savings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create and restore snapshots with a click&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add an existing domain-joined VM as a session host&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Others
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-Tenant switch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Split-Tenant mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search for unused disks and nics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollout VM Scale Sets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start and deallocate Scale Set instances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Re-image Scale Set instances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove customer-managed key (CMK)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;installation&quot;&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;release-history&quot;&gt;Release History&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 10/13/2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/fH1_FzNyJf0&quot;&gt;Check out the Youtube video to install and configure WVDAdmin in four steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;I'm continuously updating WVDAdmin to make it easier to administrate and deploy WVD, users, and session hosts. Click to see the change history.&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Release&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Changes &amp;amp; Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.05.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-10-13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for different VM sizes (Bas_v2, Bls_v2, Bats_v2, etc.); Update of the imaging script&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8.01.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-09-19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support to capture trusted launch VMs directly into an Azure Compute Gallery; More reliable rollout of session hosts working around some of the AVD-agent issues&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.63.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-07-09&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Update of the installation script to install WinGet/Microsoft Package Manager applications&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.62.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-06-28&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: New deployed hosts: In the first minutes, the correct start of the BootloaderAgent is monitored (if the service is not running, the service will be started)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.61.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-06-19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Modification to keep settings through Intune in the template&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.60.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-06-07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: In some cases a remote app icon crashed the application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.59.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-06&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Custom scirpt extension can ask for a parameter (see CustomScript-WithParameterString.ps1)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.58.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-04-07&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Ressetting the SCCM/MECM configuration during imaging; speed-up imaging for Windows 11 22H2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.57.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-04-03&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: A DLL was missing to read the Winget data (current packages)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.56.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-03-25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Update the imaging script to be even more resilient to sysprep issues. Sysprep is now monitored, and some workarounds for sysprep are triggered automatically in case of a sysprep error&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.55.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Deployment tags with an empty value are now set&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.54.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: If a larger disk size is used as the image: the last partition will be automatically extend; Add: Gallery images for Windows 10 22H2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.52.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Better handling for AAD only joined VM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.51.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Central India as meta-data location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.50.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Workaround to image Windows 11 22H2 (there is a bug in the sysprep process)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.49.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Secure boot enabled hosts are now supporting ‘Guest Attestation’ (automatically installed)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.48.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Support for Azure Disk Encryption fixed (ADE); Change to the PowerShell script: Avoiding a sysprep issue with the desired state configuration&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.47.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: GUI, overlapping checkbox for use newes agent and secure boot&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.46.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Additional Galley images; Add: Download newest AVD agent during the rollout (instead of using the agent stored in the image)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.45.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Galley images are only shown if a custom image exist&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.44.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Australia East as meta-data location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.43.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for FX-series VM size&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.42.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can filter on the ‘Virtual Machines’ by the string ‘!orphanhosts’. That shows all VMs created by WVDAdmin or Hydra as a session host but currently not part of any seen host pool (used internally the tags WVD.Path or AVD.Path); Change: Modify WVD.Path/AVD.Path in another way while moving a session host to another host pool&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.41.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Japan East as meta-data location&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.40.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Move host pool: The user assignment was not always kept;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.39.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can enable “Secure Boot” for marketplace images and for Custom Images in an Azure Compute Gallery (configure the VM image definition to support Secure Boot before copying a captured image to the gallery definition)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.38.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Deploy Azure market place images; Add: Show assigned users in the session hosts tab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.37.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Adding VM Size: NCasT4_v3-series; Add: All new created VMs are flagged to delete nic and disk if the VM is deleted in the Azure Portal&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.35.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: NoTags-mode. Prevents WVDAdmin to set the default tags on new session hosts, scale sets and images. Set HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\NoTags to 1 (NoTags is REG_DWORD32)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.34.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Having custom script for imaging and deployment based on the tenant friendly name if running in the multi-AAD-tenancy mode &lt;a href=&quot;../Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Administration-for-CSP-and-Consulting-Partners&quot;&gt;Follow this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.33.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Dark-mode. Set HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\DarkMode to 1 (DarkMode is REG_DWORD32)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.32.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Using AAD-only expected the unnecessary field domain FQDN and the rollout button was greyed out in some situations&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.31.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for NVadsA10v5 VM types&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.30.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now deploy a host in a named availability zone (normally, the zone is (optional) automatically calculate to spread hosts around different zones&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.29.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: WVDAdmin stores the last rollout configuration and now (that is new), the last image, host pool, VM-size, storage type, etc.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.28.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Gettting the diagnostic setting on a host pool changed (updated API)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.25.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Configure diagnostic settings now enables all logs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.24.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can directly re-assign a user to a VDI session host or delete an assignment (on the session host tab change or delete the user asssignment)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.23.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: A new tab shows the name of the current background processes (Jobs)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.22.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: In some cases a VM-Scale-Set Instances where not shown and crashes the application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.21.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: VM Scale Set rollout issue&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.20.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Experimental support for building session hosts based on a secure boot Golden Master&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.19.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: VM sizes for D and E series V5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.18.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Change the VM size for multiple VMs (Azure -&amp;gt; Virtual Machines); New images are created with tags including the timestamp and resource ID of the master VM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.17.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: The API permission for Azure AD Graph is no longer needed for the service principal if you are using WVDAdmin for AVD (spring edition)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.16.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Session host rollout will set an additional tag to VM, Nic and Disk: WVD.Host=&lt;Name of session host&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.15.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: If you deallocate a VM without tags, the VM is deallocate but an error message is/was shown (Changing power state of Azure vm was not successful Object reference not set to an instance of an object.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.14.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Uninstallation of th RDAgent (if you capture a session host is now faster)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.13.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Join MEM/Intune while rolling out session hosts; Add: Function to shrink a disk of a VM to 32 GByte to rollout cheaper instances and/or use smaller instances with ephemeral disks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Optimization to capture a session host for a new image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.09.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Change the rollout process to be more reliable if you deploy a lot of hosts at once; Fix: Secrets can now have special characters&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.05.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: The windows can now be resized to full-screen&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.01.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support to show subscription name in rollout and imaging tab (set HKEY_CURRENT_USER\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\ShowSubscriptionName to (reg-dword))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7.00.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support to deploy AAD-only session hosts; Fix: Resize of V2 VM disks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin_1.6.99.0.msi&quot;&gt;1.6.99.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Meta-data location for Canada and the UK&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.98.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Resize the application window height in case you have a smaller resolution (&amp;lt;828 px)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.97.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Remove a Customer Managed Key (CMK) from a VM / Disk&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.96.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for the Edv4- and Edsv4-Serie&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.95.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now use CTRL+C in each table to copy the content of the selected column&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.94.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: An import of the registry settings failed if the windows decryption key is other than the user who exported the settings&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.92.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: A session host could be visible in the session host tab of anonter hostpool if the resource id of the host pools starts with the same string&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.91.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Create and restore snapshots of a VM (right click the VM in the Azure node)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.90.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Function to shrink a disk of a VM to 64 GByte to rollout cheaper instances and/or use smaller instances with ephemeral disks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.89.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Workaround to fix an issue in the Azure API querying VM. In subscriptions with a lot of VMs an error message could given back from the API which will be workaround with this version. Original error message from Azure: Resource provider ‘Microsoft.Compute’ failed to return collection response for type ‘virtualMachines’&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.88.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Option to rollout virtual machines based on an image without joining to WVD/AVD (for servers, new golden masters, …), Update: Newest PowerShell script for generalizing and deployment to 3.0: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/AutoUpdate/Scripts/ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&quot;&gt;ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.87.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Option to switch on “Power on connect” for pooled (and assigned) host pools (preview feature)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.86.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Option to directly roll-out new session hosts with actice Azure Disk Encryption (ADE) - See “secret features” below&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.83.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Update of ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1 - if you run it from a share with prepared MSIs, the MSIs are ignored and downloaded directly from Microsoft&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.82.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Script to enable screen capture protection per session host&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.81.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Localized time for the session list (WVD classic)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.80.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Message box before logging users off&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.79.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: VM list in the “Virtual Machines” node are now showing the private IP&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.77.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Official support for meta-data regions: West Europe and North Europe&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.76.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: New applications failed to create in an existing application group&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.75.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: In some cases session hosts are not displayed in the session hosts node (no matching resource id - upper-case / lower-case issue)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.73.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Automatically change the disk type on start/stop: Add a tag “&lt;a href=&quot;../Changing-the-disk-type-automatically-while-starting-or-deallocating-a-session-host,-VM-for-WVD&quot;&gt;WVD.AdvDiskType&lt;/a&gt;” to a VM with the value “StandardSSD_LRS” or “Premium_LRS”. On the stop, the disk is converted to HDD (lowes costs), and on start, the disk is converted to the named type.  Works only with WVDAdmin (not from the Azure Portal or scaling solutions)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.72.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Fix for a sysprep failure (Sysprep data was marked corrupt; cannot proceed) in the ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1 script; Add: Better handling for shutdown/start/delete VM tasks in the Virtual Machines node&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.71.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: The disk size for new session hosts can be selected (optional) to have a higher IOPS performance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.70.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: For preview only: Checkbox to enable upcoming “Start on connect feature”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.69.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Open files are not shown if different storage accounts in different subscriptions are used under some circumstances&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.68.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: West Europe as metadata location (can only be used if the subscription is in an appropriate preview program); Add: Some scroll bars to list boxes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.66.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Rollout from session hosts based on a share image gallery item failed in another subscription then the subscription containing the gallery image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.65.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Security query before hosts are started, stopped or restarted&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.64.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Install session host optionally with Azure Monitor Extension or sepago Azure Monitor (for Azure Monitor Extension: Make sure that you have configured the target host pool correctly once: Right-click -&amp;gt; Configure Diagnostic settings)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.62.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now terminate file handles to an Azure Storage (orphaned handles avoiding a user to log in with its FSLogix profile) - Service Principal needs contributor permissions to the storage account&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.61.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: VC++ runtime if you use the destkop installer&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.60.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Manage your Virtual Machines like session hosts: Click on Azure - Virtual Machines to list all VMs in your subscriptions (note: data for the VMs are are delayed (resource graph))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.59.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Rollback of advanced logging of create VM / create Image Powershell script: Shows unimportand messages as an error with existing images&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.57.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can enable diagnostic settings directly on a host pool, appgroup and workspace (right-click); Fix: Sometimes reading the state of a script extension is not directly possible. This cause that the WVDAdmin log shows an error even if everything works as expected&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.56.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Single session nodes are not listed under the session host node if more then 100 sessions exist to speed up WVDAdmin - all sessions are still in the session list&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.54.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Function to delete unused disks and nics; Add: More logging for the rollout of session hosts; Add: New VM-types, like L4s_v2, …&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.53.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Add session hosts automatically to Loadbalancer Backend Pools; Add: If a VM resource is unavailable, the first alternative VM size will be tried&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.51.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Custom script to install &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sepago.de/en/azure-monitor-en&quot;&gt;Azure Monitor for WVD from sepago&lt;/a&gt; to existing session hosts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.50.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Dhsv3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.46.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now rollout new session hosts with accelerated network configuration, Change: NICs are now created with the name of the VM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.45.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Add session hosts automatically to ASGs&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin_1.6.42.msi&quot;&gt;1.6.42.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Dasv4-series&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.41.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Experimental feature: Add applications to session hosts from Windows Package Manager repository&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.40.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: Having a script-path for building images is no longer needed. If you leave the text box empty, the local script coming with WVDAdmin will be used and directly send to the VM&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.35.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: On a session host &amp;gt; State &amp;gt; Mouse over will show the health report of the host&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.34.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: The drop-down list “Feature release” was not shown correctly. Feature release is the selector between the different WVD/AVD versions like Fall (WVD classic) and Spring (WVD modern on ARM)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.32.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can run scripts on multiple classic session hosts: Win Updates: Install new available updates; Custom script: Custom script located in the program files folder of WVDAdmin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.30.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Sorting order for WVD/AVD resources&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.29.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Eav4 and Easv4-series&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.28.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Speed up adding a lot of VMs to the treeview&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.27.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for using availability zones. Select it from the drop-down list right to the resource group list&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.26.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can run scripts on multiple ARM session hosts: Win Updates: Install new available updates; Custom script: Custom script located in the program files folder of WVDAdmin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.24.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Multi selection and action on session hosts for ARM if you select a session host container; Fix: Scale Set instances wasn’t shown in 1.6.23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.23.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: New image was not visualized in the tree view after creation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.22.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for shared image galleries: Add a shared image gallery from the Azure Portal into a resource group managed by WVDAdmin. In WVDAdmin right-click an existing image and select “copy to shared image gallery”. An image can be rolled-out right clicking the shared image&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.21.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Double-click on the tag Logs, Sessions or Sessions V2 enlarge the part of the windows (double-click again to revert)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.18.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: API change from Microsoft cause that updating a host pool property fails if the location is written like “Central US” (centralus is no problem); Add: First version able to deploy session hosts from images in a image gallery&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.16.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Session hosts icons  are now based on the availability state; Fix: Enumerating thousands of sessions with thousands of session hosts takes longer as expected (&amp;gt; 4 minutes)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.14.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support US Government Cloud. Activate: Add a new string Reg_SZ “Environment” with value “US” to HKCU\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.12.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for VM types: Dv4 and Dsv4-series, Ev4 and Esv4-series&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.11.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: WVD/AVD ARM resources are deployed with the tags; Workspaces and host pools are separated by subscription name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.9.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Generating toke for Spring host pool fails sometimes (Error: ExpirationTime value must be between one hour and 30 days from now”  - An error occurred while gathering an WVD2 token from backend: Object reference not set to an instance of an object.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.5.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for DD_v2 and DDS_V4 virtual machine types; Fix: Forwarding from the WVD/AVD API cause a authentication lost (error 401, 403 reading resources in the FALL update)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for GEN2 virtual machines&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.2.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: New naming feature for new session host. Default (is): Name for a session host is the highest matching name +1; new concept (must be enabled): Name for a session host is the next free name. To enable add a reg dword to HKCU\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin Name:NamingMode and value to “1”&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Default session limit for V2 host pool is now 999999&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6.0.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Change: The tag WVD.Path is aligned to Microsoft naming of “tenant” and “host pool” for the spring update. Tenant=resource group name and no longer subscription name&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.9.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Load assigned users button to the app group tab (fall update)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.7.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can join existing VM’ to a host pool (VMs must be domain joined and not in a host pool right now)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.6.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: You can now move session host around host pools not created with WVDAdmin (it downloads the necessary files automatically); you can join existing VM’ to a host pool (VMs must be domain joined)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.5.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Enumerating VMs was endless in some circumstance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Migration from Fall to Spring Update; moving session hosts to another host pool&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.3.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Improvement updating the treeview&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5.0.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Spring-Update,-Spring-Release&quot;&gt;Supporting the WVD Spring Release / Spring Update&lt;/a&gt; ; Some user operations from the session grid are now async; Fix: Spontaneous resize of the windows if data are reloaded&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.9.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Filter users, session hosts and host pools in the overview of sessions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.8.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support to add users by groups from Azure Active Directory, including an AAD browser (check my &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Add-Users-and-Groups-to-WVD/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; and configure the service principal to use this feature)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.6.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: New VM sizes; all new scale sets are deployed as really scalable version (up to 600 instances each)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Service Principal Keys with some special characters are working now; Add: Faster loading of resources from WVD/AVD and Azure backend&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.2.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for NVv4 VM sizes (based on AMD Radeon Instinct  MI25-GPU); support to set custom Azure tags for resources while deploying resources&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4.0.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: From an older version, disks are deployed as standard-hdd even if premium-disk was selected; Change: Connection views are now located parallel to the logging list on the bottom (tenant-view); Add: Function to check for an updated version via &lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin.xml&quot;&gt;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/WVDAdmin.xml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.6.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: New tag for session hosts: WVD.Path - used by &lt;a href=&quot;http://loganalytics.sepago.com/&quot;&gt;Azure Monitor for WVD&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/Project-MySmartScale&quot;&gt;Azure Autoscale for WVD - aka Project MySmartScale&lt;/a&gt; if an installed language pack conflicts with the Microsoft RDAgent (read this &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Language-Packs-Detecting-Host-Pool-and-Tenant-Name/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; to learn more)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.5.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Allow an local admin to shadow a user session (WVDAdmin needs direct access to the session host via RDP)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Networks are now listed as VNET/SUBNET in the rollout tab&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.3.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for a special mode if your WVD/AVD tenant and the session hosts in two different Azure Active Directory tenants&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: WVDAdmin crashed if 1.3.0 is your first version of WVDAdmin (HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud doesn’t exist while checking for multi-tenancy mode)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3.0.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: AAD multi-tenancy mode (drop down list to handle different AADs) - &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Administration-for-CSP-and-Consulting-Partners/&quot;&gt;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Administration-for-CSP-and-Consulting-Partners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.8.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: If you click a tenant a tenant wide list of sessions is listed.  Logoff or send messages to multiple sessions&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.7.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: The main window of the application is now resizeable&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.5.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for Scale Sets (with normal and ephemeral disks) -&amp;gt; see below&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.4.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for availability sets&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.3.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Support for automatic and static assigned host pools&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2.1.00&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;v121-note&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Fix: Logging of rollout parameter by Azure custom extension is removed to avoid logging secrets&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.30&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Rollout - OU can now be empty to join the default OU&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.29&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Supporting “special license mode” to save up to 50% on compute-cost (&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/apply-windows-license&quot;&gt;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/apply-windows-license&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Template VM can now be a VM with a standard disk (non-managed)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.25&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: If you delete a VM the OS disk will deleted as well&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.23&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Support for ephemeral  disks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.0.0.22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First published version - without auto-update of WVDAdmin&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;configuration&quot;&gt;Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;service-principal-functional-account&quot;&gt;Service principal (functional account)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To work with the GUI, you need a service principal (function account) with permission to administrate access to the AVD and Azure resources. I decide to use a service principal to avoid confusion if my Azure AD user is only a guest account in the AVD tenant I have to administrate and easily switch between different tenants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a service principal, go to your Azure AD -&amp;gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.azure.com/#blade/Microsoft_AAD_IAM/ActiveDirectoryMenuBlade/RegisteredApps&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;App registration&lt;/a&gt; -&amp;gt; New registration and type a name for your principal like “ svc_WVDAdmin” and press “register”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-001.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on “certificates &amp;amp; secrets”. Click “new client secret”, select a validity period and a description (like “Key01”). Press “add”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-002.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-002&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copy the generated key directly - it will never be displayed again. Note the key for later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-003.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assign users to app groups, the service principal needs one API permissions to get the users and groups from Azure AD (optional):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the permission “Microsoft Graph” -&amp;gt; Application Permission -&amp;gt; Directory.Read.All&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/SP-PermissionToReadDirectoryObjects-01b.png&quot; alt=&quot;AADBrowser&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To consent, the permission and administrator of Azure AD have to grant this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/SP-PermissionToReadDirectoryObjects-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;AADBrowser&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go to “Overview”. Note the “Application (client) ID” and the “Directory (tenant) ID” as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-004.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-004&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You now have all data for your service principal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tenant id&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service principal id (application id)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service principal key&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;avd-permissions&quot;&gt;AVD permissions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter is for AVD ARM / Spring. &lt;a href=&quot;#azure-resource-permissions&quot;&gt;Skip&lt;/a&gt; this chapter if you only work with WVD Classic (Fall).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service principal needs permission to add and modify AVD resource objects (host pools, workspaces, app groups). To assign users and groups to app groups, the service principal needs the owner role on the resource groups you want to use for your AVD environment. Add the service principal in the next step and use the &lt;strong&gt;owner&lt;/strong&gt; role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;register-resource-provider&quot;&gt;Register Resource Provider&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have never worked with AVD, you have to register the AVD resource provider once. To do that, go to the Azure portal -&amp;gt; subscriptions -&amp;gt; select your subscription -&amp;gt; Resource providers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search for “Microsoft.DesktopVirtualization” and click on “Register”.
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-015.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-015&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;azure-resource-permissions&quot;&gt;Azure resource permissions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service principal needs permission to subscriptions or resource groups to manage your AVD resources, imaging template VM and rollout session hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open the Azure portal and go to the resource groups you want to use or to the subscriptions. In each resource group/subscription, click “Access control (IAM)” -&amp;gt; select “Add” -&amp;gt; Add role assignment. Select “owner” and search in “Select” for your service principal name. Click on the principal and save the settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Owner is needed to assign users to app groups. For other resources, “contributor” is fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-006.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-006&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The service principal must have permissions to your virtual network (vnet) to assign new VMs to the right subnet. Go to your vnet, click “Access control (IAM)” -&amp;gt; select “Add” -&amp;gt; Add role assignment. Select “contributor” and search in “select” for your service principal name. Click the principal and save the settings. You could skip this step if you assigned the service principal to the subscription or to the resource group containing your vnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-007.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-007&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;prepare-your-native-active-directory&quot;&gt;Prepare your “native” Active Directory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today each session host must be part of a “native” active directory domain (or have to use the domain services). To add new session hosts unattended, we need an administrative user account to add a computer object to the active directory domain. You can use an existing one, or you can create a new service user:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open “Active Directory Users and Computers” and create a user object with a complex password, and set a password to “never expire” (if you fine with this). I added the user &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:srv_WVD-Join@itprocloud.de&quot;&gt;srv_WVD-Join@itprocloud.de&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Delegate permission for the user to an OU. I found a really good blog post from &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/prajwaldesai&quot;&gt;Prajwal Desai&lt;/a&gt;. Check out hist post on (external web site): &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.prajwaldesai.com/allow-domain-user-to-add-computer-to-domain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Method 2 – Delegate rights to user/group using Active Directory Users and Computers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case I added my function account to: “OU=WVD,OU=Azure,OU=Site,OU=Servers,OU=Sys,OU=Organisation,DC=ITProCloud,DC=test”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;optional-create-a-file-share&quot;&gt;Optional: Create a file share&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In earlier versions (&amp;lt;1.6.40), you had to provide the deployment script and the AVD agent binaries on a custom file share or blob storage. With WVDAdmin 1.6.40 or newer, this no longer mandatory.
In some cases, where virtual machines don’t have access to the internet to download the AVD agent binaries, you can use a custom file share.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Read more.&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hint: Alternatively, you can use Azure blob storage to store the script. Make the blob storage read-only and use the URL as rollout script-path. E.g.: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sharedservices01.blob.core.windows.net/wvd&quot;&gt;https://sharedservices01.blob.core.windows.net/wvd&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a file share for the configuration script (which adds new session hosts to the domain and install the AVD agent). Give everyone at least read permissions. Set the NTFS permissions to everyone and read. This is necessary while during the first startup, the VM extension tries to execute the script. In this process, the file share is accessed anonymously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-009.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-009&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-010.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-010&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Place the following files in this share:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/AutoUpdate/Scripts/ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&quot;&gt;ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1&lt;/a&gt; (rename the download to .ps1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://query.prod.cms.rt.microsoft.com/cms/api/am/binary/RWrmXv&quot;&gt;Microsoft.RDInfra.RDAgent.msi&lt;/a&gt; (rename the file)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://query.prod.cms.rt.microsoft.com/cms/api/am/binary/RWrxrH&quot;&gt;Microsoft.RDInfra.RDAgentBootLoader.msi&lt;/a&gt; (rename the file)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure that you rename the files to fit the list above (without version numbers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-011.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-011&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Important:&lt;/strong&gt; If you are using Windows Server &lt;strong&gt;2019&lt;/strong&gt; as file share, make sure that anonymous file share access is enabled. Create a GPO for the session hosts containing the following configurations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security Options:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accounts: Guest Account Status: Enabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network access: Let Everyone permissions apply to anonymous users: Enabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network access: Do not allow anonymous enumeration of SAM accounts and shares: Disabled&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;configure-wvdadmin&quot;&gt;Configure WVDAdmin&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please start WVDAdmin. Before you load AVD and Azure data, copy the Azure tenant id, service principal id, and service principal key into the welcome tab. Press save and load the data by clicking “Reload all”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are now able to administrate WVD, create images from template VMs and rollout new session hosts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time you want to roll out new session hosts, you have to enter some information from your Active Directory and file share configuration from above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-012.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-012&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Local Admin and local pw. are the local administrator account credentials which you can enter at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-013.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-013&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;build-an-image&quot;&gt;Build an image&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can rollout VMs and VM Scale Set with images created by WVDAdmin. These images contain the logic to join the AD domain and WVD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can simple create an image from a template VM. The template VM must part of your AD like a standard client. You have not to sysprep or to normalize this template VM. Use the same template VM for Windows and application updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following these steps to build your template:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install a VM in the Azure portal. Select the right OS (like Windows 10 Enterprise for Virtual Desktops)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make all Windows updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Join the VM to your AD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Install your application&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make your customizing (like installing language packages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shutdown the template VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create the image, open WVDAdmin and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigate to the Azure template VM (Azure -&amp;gt; Virtual Machines -&amp;gt; RG -&amp;gt; VM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Right-click -&amp;gt; “Create a template image”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the resource group to store the image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Press “Capture”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can and should reuse the template VM for new updates and applications. After these changes, shut down the template VM and create a new image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;tipps-amp-tricks&quot;&gt;Tipps &amp;amp; Tricks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;vm-scale-sets&quot;&gt;VM Scale Sets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First node: VM Scale Sets cannot autoscale AVD session hosts. Auto-scaling only works for stateless services like a web server. But if you need hundreds of session hosts, then VM Scale Set allows you to work with these numbers efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Read more&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
From version 1.2.5, WVDAdmin support VM Scale Sets. A Scale Set can have several instances, which are the VMs / session hosts. There are some essential things you have to know if you use VM Scale Set with WVDAdmin and AVD itself:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a Scale Set with WVDAdmin. Select an image, right-click and select “Create session host from image”. Check “Rollout as VM Scale Set”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use regular disks and ephemeral disks. If you use ephemeral disks, you cannot deallocate the instances of your Scale Set. You have to delete the instances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Today, you can not use ultra disks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can add and remove instances with WVDAdmin or in the Azure Portal. New instances will join the domain and WVD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new instance can only join AVD if the session host with the new name doesn’t exist. If you delete instances, the session host entry will also be removed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can re-image single instances or all instances of a Scale Set. After that, the instances are “clean” as at the first rollout&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding instances or re-imaging assumes that the Scale Set configuration (which is a custom script extension) has a valid AVD token to join new instances to WVD. While AVD provides only one token per host pool and that the token can be expiring, you can update the token with a right-click on the Scale Set and select “Update WVD token”. The max. lifetime of a token is 59 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unfortunately, WVDAdmin cannot change the source image for a VM Scale Set. So if you want to update the image for a host pool, take these steps:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rollout a new Scale Set based on the new image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Disable new logons for the old session host from the previous Scale Set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Test the host pool based on the new Scale Set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If no user logged on to the ancient Scale Set, remove all instances from the Scale Set (this deletes the session hosts in AVD as well)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the Scale Set&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ephemeral--disks&quot;&gt;Ephemeral  disks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ephemeral disks are awesome. They give you a high performance free of charge. Especially in a AVD multiuser environment where no data a stored permanently on the session hosts, this kind of disk can give you some value add.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Read more&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
Ephemeral disks are running on the Azure hypervisor and not stored. This has some advantages:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are no storage costs (!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A very high data throughput because the disks exist on the hypervisor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/michawets&quot;&gt;@MichaWets&lt;/a&gt;   blog post for more information:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloud-architect.be/2019/07/15/windows-virtual-desktop-running-on-ephemeral-os-disks/&quot;&gt;https://www.cloud-architect.be/2019/07/15/windows-virtual-desktop-running-on-ephemeral-os-disks/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can not deallocate a VM with this disk type - you have to delete the VM (and roll out a new one instead of starting a “normal” VM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not each VM size is available, and there are limitations of the disk size (image size for rollout) based on the VM size: Max ephemeral disk size for  Standard_D4s_v3  is 64 GByte while a  Standard_D8s_v3 can have up to 128 GByte. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-machines/linux/sizes-general&quot;&gt;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-machines/linux/sizes-general&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the Azure hypervisor fails, your session host will fail as well and can not be re-deployed automatically&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/documentation-014.png&quot; alt=&quot;documentation-001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;secret-features&quot;&gt;Secret Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WVDAdmin has some features not directly visible but configurable via registry keys. All settings in the registry are in the current user part under HKEY_CURRENT_USER\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin. Keep in mind to restart WVDAdmin after changing the registry settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Read more&lt;/summary&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;dark-mode&quot;&gt;Dark-mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From version 1.7.33 WVDAdmin can be run in dark-mode. Set the following reg value and restart WVDAdmin: HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Software\ITProCloud\WVDAdmin\DarkMode to 1 (DarkMode is REG_DWORD32)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;multi-tenant-mode&quot;&gt;Multi-Tenant-Mode&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From version 1.3.0 WVDAdmin will support a multi-AAD-tenancy mode allowing to switch the Azure AD tenant very easily.
&lt;a href=&quot;../Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Administration-for-CSP-and-Consulting-Partners&quot;&gt;Follow this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;having-multiple-service-principals-for-a-single-tenant&quot;&gt;Having multiple Service Principals for a single Tenant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Multi-Tenant-Mode, you can add one service principal per tenant. Sometimes you need more service principals for the same tenant. You can add more service principals for a tenant if you append #1 directly behind the tenant id (or #2, …).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;naming-of-the-session-hosts&quot;&gt;Naming of the Session Hosts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you deploy session hosts to a host pool, WVDAdmin counts up the names from the highest available VM. E.g., if you have a session host with the name “WVD-PROD-012” and you rollout new hosts (WVD-PROD-###), the first new hostname is “WVD-PROD-013” - even if you have gaps in the existing numeration. You can force WVDAdmin to fill this gaps (non-existing hosts in the naming schema) if you set the following registry key:
Reg-DWord: &lt;strong&gt;NamingMode&lt;/strong&gt; = &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;split-tenant&quot;&gt;Split-Tenant&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, the AVD tenant and the resources (sessions hosts) are in the same AAD tenant. If you have two Azure AD tenant, you can use WVDAdmin with a second service principal for the session hosts (resource tenant).
&lt;a href=&quot;../Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin-for-2-tenant-mode&quot;&gt;Follow this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;us-government-cloud&quot;&gt;US-Government Cloud&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WVDAdmin can be used to deploy AVD in the Azure Government Cloud. You can enable WVDAdmin to work in the US Government Cloud via registry:
Reg-SZ: &lt;strong&gt;Environment&lt;/strong&gt; = &lt;strong&gt;US&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;run-custom-actions-simultaneously&quot;&gt;Run custom actions simultaneously&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From version 1.6.15, WVDAdmin supports custom scripts to run administrative tasks simultaneously on different session hosts. And that is easy to use and to extend.
&lt;a href=&quot;../Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin-CustomScripts&quot;&gt;Follow this link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;add-a-session-host-automatically-to-an-asg&quot;&gt;Add a session host automatically to an ASG&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add a session host automatically to application security groups (ASG) within the rollout process. To achieve this, add one or more tags to the host pool containing your new session hosts. Name &lt;strong&gt;WVD.Default.ASG.X&lt;/strong&gt; and add the azure resource id of an existing asg. X can be numbers to assign more ASGs. You can copy the id from an ASG from your browser. It looks like this: /subscriptions/&amp;lt;subscription-id&amp;gt;/resourcegroups/&amp;lt;resourcegroup-name&amp;gt;/providers/Microsoft.Network/applicationSecurityGroups/&amp;lt;asg-name&amp;gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/WVDAdmin/asg-001.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tag for ASG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;add-a-session-host-automatically-to-a-loadbalancer-backend-pool&quot;&gt;Add a session host automatically to a Loadbalancer Backend Pool&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can add a session host automatically to a loadbalancer backend pool within the rollout process. To achieve this, add one or more tags to the host pool containing your new session hosts. Name &lt;strong&gt;WVD.Default.LBPool.X&lt;/strong&gt; and add the azure resource id of an existing loadbalancer backend pool. X can be numbers to assign more ASGs. You can copy the id from a pool from your browser. It looks like this: /subscriptions/&amp;lt;subscription-id&amp;gt;/resourcegroups/&amp;lt;resourcegroup-name&amp;gt;/providers/Microsoft.Network/loadBalancers/&amp;lt;loadbalancer-name&amp;gt;/backendAddressPools/&amp;lt;pool-name&amp;gt;
Keep in mind to use availability sets for each rollout to use this feature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rollout-session-hosts-with-azure-disk-encryption-ade&quot;&gt;Rollout session hosts with Azure Disk Encryption (ADE)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set two tags to the host pool to use it: “WVD.Default.KeyVault.Id” with the resource id of the KeyVault, “WVD.Default.KeyVault.KeyUri” with the URI (including the version) of the prepared key to wrap the secret.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;create-an-image&quot;&gt;Create an Image&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The image is not created. An error message occurs:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check if your template VM part of the AD&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If your file server Windows Server 2019, read above&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check if you have set the NTFS and share permission correctly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Azure portal: Go to the temp VM (next to the template VM) and check the extension installation state. There should be an error message like script not found, access denied, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have you renamed the RD agent and bootloader?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the script saved correctly: ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1, not ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don’t forget to delete the temp VM and temp disk to avoid costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure that your template VM uses managed disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The script generates additional log files in %WinDir%\System32\LogFiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Windows 7&lt;/em&gt;: Make sure to install PowerShell 5.1 and all Windows updates (including the optional updates without the language packages) to the template VM and restart the VM to take effect: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=54616&quot;&gt;https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=54616&lt;/a&gt; Makes sure that you use the newest script file from 09/2020: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/AutoUpdate/Scripts/ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&quot;&gt;ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NEW: An endless loop of “Waiting for the temporary vm (power off)” : Update to the newest PowerShell script for generalizing: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/assets/files/AutoUpdate/Scripts/ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1.txt&quot;&gt;ITPC-WVD-Image-Processing.ps1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;others&quot;&gt;Others&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have created a host pool, an app group, and assigned a user to the app group, but the user cannot see the apps/desktop.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For AVD ARM: Don’t forget to create a workspace and link the app group in the workspace. The workspace is mandatory to show the users’ resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For the HTML5 web site: Check the correct web address:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ARM/Spring: &lt;a href=&quot;https://aka.ms/wvdarmweb&quot;&gt;https://aka.ms/wvdarmweb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Classic/Fall: &lt;a href=&quot;http://aka.ms/wvdweb&quot;&gt;http://aka.ms/wvdweb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/WVDAdmin.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 10/13/2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Debugging Azure Virtual Desktop errors/issues/network latency and bandwidth with an interactive Workbook</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Correctly configured, Azure Virtual Desktop sends diagnostic data to a log analytics workspace (Azure Monitor). There are several logs containing data about the events in the backend:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Log Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDAgentHealthStatus&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Details about the session hosts&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDConnections&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;All about connections from a user to a session host&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDErrors&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Error message from different sources (client, RDGateway, Loadbalancer, …)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDFeeds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Log about clients downloading information about the AVD resources&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDHostRegistrations&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Logs if a host tries to register to a host pool&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDManagement&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Log about administrative tasks&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDCheckpoints&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Detailed information related to logins, errors, …&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;WVDConnectionNetworkData&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Network information (bandwidth and RTT)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get the logs, configure at least the host pool to send log information to a log analytics workspace. You can do this on a host pool level -&amp;gt; Diagnostic settings -&amp;gt; Add diagnostic settings -&amp;gt; Select all Logs and target a log analytics workspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Avd-Error-Monitoring-01.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt; to do that (use version 1.7.25 or higher):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Avd-Error-Monitoring-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will take a while before you can see the first data. The data can be queried with the KUSTO language or analyzed with custom workbooks. I prepared a workbook to dig into the data. Most visualizations are interactive. So you can drill down by selecting users, networks, agent versions, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/AVD-Monitoring-Workbook-Errors.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/MonitorSessionHosts-12.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Avd-Error-Monitoring-13.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Avd-Error-Monitoring-14.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can install the workbook directly as a template into your subscription: &lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.azure.com/#create/Microsoft.Template/uri/https%3A%2F%2Fblog.itprocloud.de%2Fassets%2Ffiles%2FAzureDeployments%2FWorkbook-AVD-Error-Logging.json&quot;&gt;Install the workbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a while, the workbook is visible as a new template in: &lt;strong&gt;Log Analytics -&amp;gt; Workbooks -&amp;gt; Azure Virtual Desktop -&amp;gt; AVD - Deep-Insights&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can select the time frame and host pool from the drop-down list. The other drop-down lists are optional. Please ensure that you have included the essential errors from the error selector. Remember that not all errors are making issues (e.g., “&lt;em&gt;ConnectionFailedClientDisconnected&lt;/em&gt;” occurs if a session goes in the disconnected mode while the users close its notebook).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please let me know if you have ideas to extend the workbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Version&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;01/28/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Initial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/17/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Include RTT and bandwidth (right now, host pool must be in the validation environment and diagnostic data must include &lt;strong&gt;NetworkData&lt;/strong&gt;); see &lt;a href=&quot;https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-virtual-desktop/collect-and-query-network-data-for-azure-virtual-desktop/m-p/3140397&quot;&gt;https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/azure-virtual-desktop/collect-and-query-network-data-for-azure-virtual-desktop/m-p/3140397&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Name changed to AVD - Deep-Insights&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/16/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Include Logon timing (GPO, FSLogix, Authentication, etc.)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;04/14/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In Session Bandwidths &amp;amp; Latencies: The connection type is shown if RDP Short Path is used (Public, Private). See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/shortpath-public&quot;&gt;https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/shortpath-public&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;05/03/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;New visualization: Logon timing per day and category over the time&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/11/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;New visualization: Connections over time, unhealthy session hosts, graphic performance&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/03/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Optimization for charts to show data over a large time frame&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/14/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A new tab “Resources”, to show orphan session hosts; Fix: Number of active and inactive sessions - timeselector was not correct&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;11/18/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;A new tab “Resources”, to show orphan VMs (where the session host object is missing)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.0&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/01/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Changed the description for the estimated available bandwidth&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.1&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;12/09/2022&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Added orphan disks and orphan nics to the “Resources” tab (note: All orphand devices will also shown and could be removed in Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop, version 1.0.1.84 (comming soon))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.2&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/02/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Added “Water Markings” to query session information by the feature &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/virtual-desktop/watermarking&quot;&gt;WaterMarking&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/20/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Added “Unresponding AVD Agents” in the tab “Resources” to identify running VM with a non responding AVD agent&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;02/21/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Added new tab “FSLogix” to show the size, usage and free space of the FSLogix profiles&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/08/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix in the time selector; allow to selecte multiple host pools; show active sessions with user name and started desktop/remote app&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.6&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;03/31/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Show office container size and usage (ODFC) in the FSLogix tab (additional to the profile container)&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;07/01/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix/Workaround: VHDFreeSpace is stored as text in MByte and not in GByte if the value is less then 1 GByte&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2.8&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;10/13/2023&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add: Show the last heart beat time in the Orphan session hosts view and warns, if the heart beat is longer then 90 days ago&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://portal.azure.com/#create/Microsoft.Template/uri/https%3A%2F%2Fblog.itprocloud.de%2Fassets%2Ffiles%2FAzureDeployments%2FWorkbook-AVD-Error-Logging.json&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aka.ms/deploytoazurebutton&quot; alt=&quot;Deploy to Azure&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please click twice on create to accept the Microsoft Agreement of terms - Workbooks don’t generate costs&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Error-Drill-Down-Workbook/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/AVD-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-Error-Drill-Down-Workbook/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Monitor</category>
        
        <category>Log Analytics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Updating a Golden Master VM from Windows 10 multi-user to Windows 11 multi-user</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Golden-Master approach is a common way to deploy applications and desktops as session hosts in Azure Virtual Desktop. The approach is very simple, and the rollout of new session hosts is very fast - while applications are installed and the host configured. Using PowerShell, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra&lt;/a&gt; simplifies the process while the original Golden Master VM survives and can be updated with OS and application updates over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing the Golden Master VM in Azure with Windows multi-user
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Running Windows Update&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installing the applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configuring the VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grabbing an image with PowerShell, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra&lt;/a&gt;, etc., &lt;strong&gt;without destroying&lt;/strong&gt; the Golden Master VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using the image to deploy multiple session hosts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a very easy approach, and often, the applications and the configuration of the master are done with a software deployment solution (like Intune, ECM). But there are also deployments where the master was customized manually, including the configuration and applications. In this case, changing the underlying OS can be a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;windows-10-multi-user&quot;&gt;Windows 10 multi-user&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of manual customized Golden Masters with Windows 10 multi-user. Unfortunately, Windows Update mostly does not offer an in-place-upgrade to Windows 11 multi-user. Even the following approaches are not working for Windows 10 multi-user:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downloading Windows 11 and trying to upgrade the VM -&amp;gt; Doesn’t work, while the ISO files of Windows 11 are not multi-user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing Windows Update to install Windows 11 -&amp;gt; That is mostly not enough (see below)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;preparing-your-vm&quot;&gt;Preparing your VM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To update to Windows 11 multi-user, your VM must have trusted launch-, secure boot-enabled, and a vTPM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can do this in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your VM is Generation V1:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Migrate-Azure-V1-VM-to-Azure-V2-VM-In-A-Safe-Way/&quot;&gt;Creating a Windows Azure VM Generation V2 from a V1 VM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your VM is Generation V2 without a trusted launch-enabled security type:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Migrate-Azure-VM-To-Trusted-Launch/&quot;&gt;Updating or cloning a Azure VM with standard security to trusted launch with secure boot and vTPM&lt;/a&gt; or&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Migrate-Azure-V1-VM-to-Azure-V2-VM-In-A-Safe-Way/&quot;&gt;Creating a Windows Azure VM Generation V2 from a V1 VM&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;forcing-windows-update&quot;&gt;Forcing Windows Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can force Windows Update to show Windows 11 as an option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log in to the new Golden Master
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modify the local policy to force Windows Update to install Windows 11 22h2: Local Computer Policy\Computer Configuration\Administrative Templates\Windows Components\Windows Update\Windows Updates for Business\Select the target Feature Update version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run Windows Update&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update to Windows 11&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reboot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the local policy entries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your Golden Master is ready and converted from Windows 10 to 11 multi-user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/T8lJnepnEKk&quot;&gt;Link to the YouTube video.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/Update-11-22h2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you got the following error message: &lt;strong&gt;The PC must support TPM 2.0.&lt;/strong&gt;, you have forgotten to migrate your VM to a V2 Generation with trusted lauch-enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Update-Windows-10-Multi-user-to-Windows-11-Multi-user/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Update-Windows-10-Multi-user-to-Windows-11-Multi-user/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Azure</category>
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Updating or cloning a Azure VM with standard security to trusted launch with secure boot and vTPM</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; If your source VM is based on the &lt;strong&gt;VM generation V1&lt;/strong&gt;, follow this post to convert your VM: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Migrate-Azure-V1-VM-to-Azure-V2-VM-In-A-Safe-Way/&quot;&gt;Creating a Windows Azure VM Generation V2 from a V2 VM&lt;/a&gt;. Also, follow the link if you want to have an exact copy (and not a clone) of your VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you once installed an Azure VM with the standard of security, you can not convert this VM into a trusted launch-enabled VM with secure boot and vTPM. But that is sometimes necessary, e.g., if you want to upgrade from Windows 10 multi-user to Windows 11 multi-user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is a way to do that. You could capture your existing VM and store the image in a secure boot enabled. Compute Gallery definition in Azure. From this image version, you can create a new VM with a security-type trusted launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;prepare-an-azure-compute-gallery&quot;&gt;Prepare an Azure Compute Gallery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create an Azure Compute Gallery “Conversion_Gallery” in the same resource group of your VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add an Image Definition “Secure-VM”
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security Type: Trusted Launch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OS state: Generalized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tick “Accelerated networking” if this is enabled on your original VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill Publisher, Offer, SKU with some information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click Review+Create, Create&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/To-TrustedLaunch-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;capturing-the-original-vm&quot;&gt;Capturing the original VM&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt; to prevent that I must sysprep my original VM. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt; first makes a clone of the original VM and runs sysprep on the clone. In the end, I have an image in a compute gallery and the untouched original VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Azure -&amp;gt; Virtual Machines -&amp;gt; Resource Group -&amp;gt; Right-click the VM and select “Create a template image”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter an image name (no spaces)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the resource group of the VM as Target RG&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tick “Use Azure Compute Galleries”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select your Gallery and Gallery definition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your region from the list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit “Capture”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This will take a while to clone the VM, create an image and upload it to the image gallery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/To-TrustedLaunch-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/To-TrustedLaunch-04.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/To-TrustedLaunch-05.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: You can delete the also-created custom image (we only need the gallery image)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;deploying-a-new-secure-boot-enabled-vm-from-the-image&quot;&gt;Deploying a new secure boot-enabled VM from the image&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt; or in the Azure Portal, you can create a new VM from that image containing all the applications. Please note that the new VM has a new name and compute identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to the gallery definition in the Azure Portal and select your uploaded version.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hit + Create VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fill out all parameters and ensure that you select the security type “Trusted Launch”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/To-TrustedLaunch-06.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/To-TrustedLaunch-07.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the deployment, you have a new trusted launch-enabled VM based on your - still existing - original VM.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Migrate-Azure-VM-To-Trusted-Launch/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Migrate-Azure-VM-To-Trusted-Launch/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Azure</category>
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Creating a Windows Azure VM Generation V2 from a V1 VM</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has provided different VM sizes over the last years and also introduced the VM Generation V2 at the end of 2019. V2 VMs are different from V1 VMs and have the following advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UEFI&lt;/strong&gt; based (no longer bios-based)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhanced OS support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Faster boot and disk support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advanced Security Features&lt;/strong&gt;, like Secure Boot, which ensures the integrity of the boot process, and BitLocker encryption, which enhances data protection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I expect that the most deployed VMs are V2, but I still see older V1 versions - including in my own environment. For example, I have several Golden Masters for Azure Virtual Desktop running Windows 10 22/h2 Multi-User. We still see V1 types because of the missing simple migration path. There is no native way in the Azure Portal to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I wanted to upgrade my Windows 10 Golden Masters to Windows 11, I came to the point of discovering that Windows 11 needs a V2 generation VM (for upgrading, trusted launch, vTPM, and secure boot must also be enabled).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some research, I figured out that this is really not simple. I found a good blog post from &lt;a href=&quot;https://charbelnemnom.com/migrate-gen1-to-gen2-vms-on-azure/&quot;&gt;Charbel Nemnom&lt;/a&gt;, who provides a step-by-step solution. The solution is still complex, so I decided to write a PowerShell script to handle this complex process more easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-does-it-work&quot;&gt;How does it work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have our V1 virtual machine we want to convert. Instead of converting, we are building a new virtual machine (V2) with the converted OS disk of our V1 VM. So, in the end, we have two identical VMs: The original V1 VM and the V2 VM. If anything doesn’t work, we still have our original VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But takes some time, and the full process takes hours (for the script).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After configuring the script, the script enters the following steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deallocates the V1 VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creates the new V2 VM with the same size in the same network, optional with trusted launch, secure boot, and vTPM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Makes a snapshot of the V1 OS disk and, from the snapshot, a cloned OS disk (still V1)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creates an empty V2 disk with the same size and type as the V1 OS disk(this disk is supposed to be our converted OS disk)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attaches the empty V2 disk and the cloned V1 OS disk to the new V2 VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The script runs itself on the V2 VM
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Preparing the partitions of the attached disks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formatting the partitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capturing the cloned V1 OS partition using DISM (that takes some time; in my last conversion, it took nearly 4 hours)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apply the captured image to the prepared partition of the empty V2 disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write the UEFI partition of the formerly empty V2 disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deallocates the V2 VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Detach the attached disks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Swap the OS disk with the no longer empty V2 disk (the now converted OS disk of the V1 VM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting the V2 VM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Doing some cleanup: Deleting the snapshot, the old V2 OS disk, the cloned V1 OS disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Done&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/V1-V2-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-use-the-script&quot;&gt;How to use the script&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open the script in a PowerShell editor like ISE (or VS Code). Connect to your Azure subscription using &lt;em&gt;Connect-AzAccount&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modify the script to match your:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your subscription Id&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your source V1 VM (name and resource group)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Your new V2 VM (name and resource group - ensure to have a different name or resource group; another name of the VM doesn’t reflect the computer name after the process)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set $enabledTrustedLaunch = $true to also create your V2 VM trusted launch enabled, incl. secure boot and vTPM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tempDiskSizeGb must be large enough to contain the temporary OS (Server 2022) and the content of the OS disk of the V1 VM (512 should be fine if the disk of the V1 VM is 128 GByte)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s all. You can run the script and come back after some hours to see the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;hints&quot;&gt;Hints&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the VM size doesn’t support V2, modify the target VM size in the script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If something fails: Cleanup the temporarily created resources manually (snapshot, empty V2 disk, cloned V1 disk, and V2 VM)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgrading to Windows 11 multi-user: Check-out this video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-is-the-script&quot;&gt;Where is the script&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the script on github: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/MarcelMeurer/aab2ef8f36d7c634beebea771f54bf30&quot;&gt;Create-V2-From-V1-VM.ps1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 07 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Migrate-Azure-V1-VM-to-Azure-V2-VM-In-A-Safe-Way/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Migrate-Azure-V1-VM-to-Azure-V2-VM-In-A-Safe-Way/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Azure</category>
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Onboard AVD pooled session hosts to Defender automatically with a script</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Onboarding session hosts to Defender is very important for security reasons. Microsoft has documented the way to onboard these devices in different scenarios here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/security/defender-endpoint/configure-endpoints-vdi&quot;&gt;https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/security/defender-endpoint/configure-endpoints-vdi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I often work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MarcelMeurer/WVD-Hydra&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt; and also have some AAD native deployment, I decided to prepare an easy script to onboard this device automatically after the rollout. The script is generic, so it can also be used with other automation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, we need the  VDI onboarding script for non-persistent devices from &lt;a href=&quot;htps://defender.microsoft.com/securitysettings/endpoints/onboarding&quot;&gt;htps://defender.microsoft.com/securitysettings/endpoints/onboarding&lt;/a&gt; - Make sure to download the right package.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install Defender without the need to store the package (zip file) to share, we can encode the package to a base64 encoded string. After that, we can grab the string from the text file &lt;em&gt;WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage.zip.txt&lt;/em&gt; and put it into quotes in line 30.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Step-by-step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Save the PowerShell script to your local disk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change &lt;em&gt;$false&lt;/em&gt; into &lt;em&gt;$true&lt;/em&gt; in line 22&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the onboarding script and store it in the same folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run the PowerShell script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open the text file &lt;em&gt;WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage.zip.txt&lt;/em&gt; and put it into quotes in line 30&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script can then be run after the rollout to join the device to Defender. In Hydra, you can add the script as a new script into Scripts and Collections (with your onboarding script encoded in line 25 and $false in line 22).
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/AVD-DefenderOnboarding-02.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add the script to the Deployment Configuration -&amp;gt; Run script or script collection after deployment:
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/images/AVD-DefenderOnboarding-03.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next device is automatically onboarded to Defender.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-script&quot;&gt;The script:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;# Script to prepare and onboard AVD non-persistent hosts to Microsoft Defender

# test if fuction LogWriter available
if (!(Test-Path function:LogWriter)) {
    function LogWriter($message) {
        Write-Host $message
    }
}
Add-Type -AssemblyName System.IO.Compression.FileSystem

$DefenderFile=&amp;quot;WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage.zip&amp;quot;
$ScriptPath = Split-Path -Path $MyInvocation.MyCommand.Definition -Parent

function UnzipFile
{
    param([string]$zipfile, [string]$out)
    [System.IO.Compression.ZipFile]::ExtractToDirectory($zipfile, $out)
}


// set it to $true to generate the base64 string from your dowloaded WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage.zip - that must run locally
if ($false) {
    # Generate base64 file fron DefenderFile
    # Download VDI onboarding script for non-persistent devices from: https://defender.microsoft.com/securitysettings/endpoints/onboarding
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Generate base64 file fron DefenderFile&amp;quot;)
    $WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage=[System.Convert]::ToBase64String((Get-Content -Path &amp;quot;$ScriptPath\$DefenderFile&amp;quot; -Encoding Byte))
    $WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage | Out-File &amp;quot;$ScriptPath\$($DefenderFile).txt&amp;quot; -Encoding UTF8
} else {
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Read base64 file fron DefenderFile&amp;quot;)
    $WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage =&amp;quot;&amp;lt;put your base64 encoded string here&amp;gt;&amp;quot;
    # Clean up the temp folder
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Cleaning up the temp folder&amp;quot;)
    Remove-Item -Path &amp;quot;$env:temp\WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage.zip&amp;quot; -Force -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
    Remove-Item -Path &amp;quot;$env:temp\WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage&amp;quot; -Recurse -Force -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Create the Defender files&amp;quot;)
    Set-Content -Path &amp;quot;$env:temp\WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage.zip&amp;quot; -Value ([System.Convert]::FromBase64String($WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage)) -Encoding Byte
    UnzipFile &amp;quot;$env:temp\WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage.zip&amp;quot; &amp;quot;$env:temp\WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage&amp;quot; 
    
    # start the test.cmd with cmd.exe in the extracted folder
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Starting the onboarding&amp;quot;)
    Start-Process -FilePath &amp;quot;$env:windir\system32\cmd.exe&amp;quot; -ArgumentList &amp;quot;/c WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingScript.cmd&amp;quot; -WorkingDirectory &amp;quot;$env:temp\WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage&amp;quot; -Wait -PassThru

    # Clean up the temp folder
    LogWriter(&amp;quot;Cleaning up the temp folder&amp;quot;)
    Remove-Item -Path &amp;quot;$env:temp\WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage.zip&amp;quot; -Force -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
    Remove-Item -Path &amp;quot;$env:temp\WindowsDefenderATPOnboardingPackage&amp;quot; -Recurse -Force -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 22 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Rollout-AVD-SessionHost-To-Defender-Automatically-with-a-script/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Rollout-AVD-SessionHost-To-Defender-Automatically-with-a-script/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Session hosts are not available in Azure Virtual Desktop, but VMs are running. </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;During June/July, I got several emails that session hosts were not available in AVD, but the VMs were in a running state. Rebooting the host sometimes helps, and the host was shown as available. We figured out that the issue was caused by a not running RDAgentBootLoader service on affected hosts. Starting the service (or the host) resolved the issue. Right now, I don’t know the root cause of why the RDAgentBootLoader was not started or failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To workaround this behavior by implementing a scheduled task, start with the host and monitors the service for the first 30 minutes. The service will be started if it’s not running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scheduled task will automatically be created for new deployments with &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Hydra-for-Azure-Virtual-Desktop-AVD-is-available-in-the-Azure-Marketplace/&quot;&gt;Hydra for Azure Virtual Desktop&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.itprocloud.de/Windows-Virtual-Desktop-Admin/&quot;&gt;WVDAdmin&lt;/a&gt;) from version 06/27/2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to build your own scheduled task, you can use this script:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;	$interval=30
	$run=$true
	$counter=0
	$serviceName=&amp;quot;RDAgentBootLoader&amp;quot;
	do {
		Start-Sleep -Seconds $interval
		$service=Get-Service -Name $serviceName -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
		if ($service -ne $null -and $service.Status -ne [System.ServiceProcess.ServiceControllerStatus](4)) {
			Write-Host &amp;quot;Starting service: $serviceName&amp;quot;
			Start-Service -Name $serviceName -ErrorAction SilentlyContinue
		}
		$counter++
		if ($counter -gt 10) {$interval=90}
		if ($counter -gt 20) {$run=$false}
	} while ($run)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Maybe it makes sense to monitor the service during the runtime of the VM in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/Session-Hosts-are-unavailable-or-shutdown-even-if-the-VMs-are-running/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/Session-Hosts-are-unavailable-or-shutdown-even-if-the-VMs-are-running/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CountrySwitch - First Logon Experience and language selector and an app starter for remote apps on network paths for AVD</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-logon-experience-and-language-selector-and-an-app-starter-for-remote-apps-on-network-paths&quot;&gt;First Logon Experience and language selector and an app starter for remote apps on network paths&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/CountrySwitch.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 05/11/2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;select-the-language-users&quot;&gt;Select the language (users)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In some environments, customers are running Azure on Windows 10/11 with multiple language packs installed. After the first login, users have to choose their language to customize the environment - that is not so easy, while users have to open the language settings and select the language. The first steps are outside the user’s language and are not easy to do for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I built a tool that makes it easier for users to select their language by clicking on the right flag. Currently, the following features are available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feature regarding the language selection:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tool shows the installed language packages by a flag of the countries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A welcome message in the present language welcomes the users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The user selects the language settings with a click on the flag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hovering the mouse over a flag shows the country and language name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The app configures the language settings (and does one logoff to apply the setting).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The PowerShell script CountrySwitch-User.ps1 in the program files folder is started to do some optional customizing (language code is in $languageTag)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CountrySwitch is linked in all users’ start menu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Startup: With parameter /RunOnce - Starts CountrySwitch at logon. The user will see the language selector only if the user is new and didn’t select a language once (HKCU:\SOFTWARE\ITProCloud\CountrySwitch\Completed is set to 1 )&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Direct: Without parameters - Users can star CountrySwitch manually to select the language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note on Remote Apps&lt;/strong&gt;: Remote apps are ignoring the autostart folder. To have CountrySwitch enabled for remote app, please configure a local Startup script (local policy for users) with the following parameters:
Name of script: “C:\Program Files\ITProCloud.de\CountrySwitch\CountrySwitch.exe”
Parameters:	/runonce&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;app-starter-for-remote-apps&quot;&gt;App Starter for remote apps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CountrySwitch can also start a local or an application on a file share (which normally does not work directly with AVD). Publish CountrySwitch as a remote app with the following parameters:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CountrySwitch.exe /remoteapp &amp;quot;&amp;lt;path to executable with parameters&amp;gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&amp;lt;Working directory&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;CountrySwitch.exe /remoteapp &amp;quot;\\&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;share&amp;gt;\finance.exe /db=vm1&amp;quot; &amp;quot;\\&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;share&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a remote app is started with CountrySwitch, CountrySwitch first starts the PowerShell script CountrySwitch-App.ps1 in the program files folder to do some optional customization. The following parameters are set in the script:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$languageTag = &amp;quot;unknown&amp;quot;,
$appCommandline = &amp;quot;\\&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;share&amp;gt;\finance.exe /db=vm1&amp;quot;,
$appWorkingDir = &amp;quot;\\&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;\&amp;lt;share&amp;gt;&amp;quot;,
$appParameter = &amp;quot;/db=vm1&amp;quot;,
$appExecutable = &amp;quot;finance.exe&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The application starts after the PowerShell script finishes (CountrySwitch will run hidden and terminates after the start of the application (e.g., finance.exe).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;logging-and-configuration&quot;&gt;Logging and configuration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CountrySwitch logs into %AppData%\ITProCloud&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are the following reg keys to optionally configure CountrySwitch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HKLM:\SOFTWARE\Policies\ITProCloud\CountrySwitch (alls values are dword - 1 is true; 0 is false)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Default value&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Enabled&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If false, the application will not show up (except for /remoteapp (App starter mode))&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ExitOnRunOnceCompleted&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If the app is started with /runonce and the user has already completed the process, the application will not show up&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;ExitOnSingleLanguage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If only one language is installed, don’t show up&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LogoffUserAfterSelectingNewLanguage logoff user after selecting a new language&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;LogoffUserAfterSelectingSameLanguage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Logoff user after selecting the same language as the user is still using&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;false&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;RunUserScriptAfterSelectingLanguage&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Runs the ps script CountrySwitch-User.ps1 -languageTag {xx-YY} after the user selects a language&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;DisableUserScriptForAppStarterMode&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If true, the app starter mode for a remote app will no longer trigger CountrySwitch-App before starting the application&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;true&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;release-notes&quot;&gt;Release notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Release&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Date&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Changes &amp;amp; Notes&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1.3&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-04&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Initial&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1.4&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Update: CountrySwitch-User.ps1 had a typo&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1.1.7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2023-05-11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Fix: Avoid showing MSI installation screen for users if package unaccessible&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../assets/files/CountrySwitch.msi&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../assets/icons/download.png&quot; alt=&quot;Download&quot; /&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Download the latest release from 05/11/2023&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to send me ideas for improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://blog.itprocloud.de/CountrySwitch-Select-Language-on-first-start-and-an-appstarter-for-remoteapps/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.itprocloud.de/CountrySwitch-Select-Language-on-first-start-and-an-appstarter-for-remoteapps/</guid>
        
        
        <category>Windows Virtual Desktop</category>
        
        <category>Azure Virtual Desktop</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
